I wish you wouldn't do that around me. It's so filthy !
مي شه اين کار رو جلوي من انجام ندي حالم داره بهم مي خوره
- Don't give me a problem about the cigarettes. - It's such a filthy habit.
من با سيار مشکلي ندارم عادت بديه
Oh, my God ! Look at this.
خداي من اونجارو
Oh, Jesus ! This is so appalling !
ناه کن قدر زشت و بي ريخته
I can't believe it !
باورم نمي شه
I can't believe they gave it to him.
باورم نمي شه که اونها اينو بهش دادند
Ah, this is pathetic !
آدم دلش مي سوزه
Now he's a loser with a Jaguar.
هي وقت از جکوار هم شانس نداشت
Seriously, who did he have to blow to get that thing ?
کي مجبورش کرده سوار اين لن بشه؟
- Good morning, sir. - Mr. Willis.
صبح بخير آقا آقاي ويليس
- It's really, uh, - Mr. Trask !
بدو برو آقاي تسک
quite a piece of machinery.
عين يه ربات مي مونه
- Good morning, Havemeyer. - Morning to you, sir.
صبحت بخير هيومير صبح شما هم بخير
- Bene ! - Bene ?
معرکه ست معرکه؟
- Bene ! Fabulous ! - What's fabulous ?
معرکه، عاليه ي عاليه؟
That fine piece of steel you have back there.
اون آهن قراضه اي که با خودتون آورديد اينجا
Ah, you don't think I deserve it.
آهان فکر مي کني که بهم نمي ياد
No, sir. On the contrary. I think it's great.
نه قربان اصلا ، در عوض فکر مي کنم که خيلي هم عالي و خوبه
Should the headmaster of Baird be seen putt-putting around in some junker ?
فکر نمي کنيد که مدير مدرسه اونو بايد به آلمانيها مي داد؟
In fact, I think the board of trustees have had...
در واقع فکر مي کنم بعضي اوقات همين فکر هايي
their first, true stroke of inspiration in some time.
به سر هيات امنا مي زنه تا طرفو رو خورد کنه
Thank you, Havemeyer. I'll take that at face value.
ممنونم هيومير حتما اين مسئله رو در نظر مي يرم
I'd expect nothing less, sir.
من هم يزي جز اين انتظار ندارم قربان
Have a good day.
روز خوبي داشته باشيد
- Morning, Mrs. Hunsaker. - Good morning.
صبح بخير خانم هانسيکر صبح بخير
What have we here, Murderer's Row ?
ببين اينجا توي جاياه قاتلين ي داريم؟
- What was that about ? - Nothing. Just saying hello.
ي توش بود؟ هيي، فقط يه سلام
I like to say hello to Headmaster Trask.
دلم مي خواد به آقاي ترسک سلام کنم
Sugarbush. Lift tickets and condo vouchers.
شوربراش بدش به من ببينم هزينه و ولش ه جوريه
- I thought we were goin' to Stowe. - Sugarbush is Stowe, Jimmy.
فکر مي کردم مي ريم به استو جيمي شوربراش همون استو هست
We're doing it right. Thanksgiving in Vermont, Christmas in Switzerland --
برنامه مون عاليه مراسم شکرزاري توي ورمونت، کريسمس هم توي سوئيس
-Christmas in Gstaad is gonna cost us -- -'Staad.
کريسمس توي "جي اشتاد" برامون خيلي رون تموم ميشه اشتاد
The "G" is silent. 'Staad. George ?
جي يه جزيره ست اشتاد، جرج؟
- 'Staad. - Trent ?
اشتاد ترنت؟
- 'Staad, man. - So what about 'Staad ?
اشتاد سر خب ديه ي مي خواي در مورد اشتاد بدوني؟
Fine. The "G" may be silent,
باشه، جي مي تونه يه جزيره باشه
but it's gonna take at least three grand to get there.
اما ما بايد بليط درجه سه بيريم
- I'll talk to my father. - Better yet, have my father talk to your father.
من با درم صحبت مي کنم شايد بهتر باشه در من با درت صحبت کنه
Or my father
يا اينکه در تو با در من
You goin' home this weekend, Chas ?
اين هفته ميري خونه ارلي؟
Uh, I don't know.
هان ،نمي دونم
You goin' home to fuckin' Idaho for Thanksgiving ?
براي شکرزاري ميري به اون ايداهوي لعنتي آره؟
I'm from Oregon.
من اهل ارون هستم
I meant fuckin' Oregon.
خب همون ارون لعنتي
-Charlie, how do you feel about skiing ? -[ Laughing ]
ارلي نظرت راجع به اسکي بازي يه؟
You in the mood for the white-bosomed slopes of Vermont ?
مي ري توي ته هاي برفي ورمونت اسکي مي کني، نظرت يه؟
Got a deal going. 20% off for my friends.
يه يشنهاد بهت بيشتر از دوستام تخفيف 20درصد مي دم
My father set it up. Christmas in Switzerland.
درم ترتيبش رو مي ده کريسمس هم ميريم سوئيس
- 'Staad. - Gstaad. Dropping the "G" is phony.
اشتاد جي اشتاد، جي رو جا انداختي
- You said everybody says 'Staad. - Not if you've been there.
خودت فتي که همه بهش مين اشتاد اه تو بخواي بي غلطه
Easter in Bermuda, then Kentucky Derby weekend.
عيد اک هم ميريم برمودا بعدش هم آخر هفته ميريم کنتکي درباي
We could fit you in, kid.
هي سر مي تونيم تورو هم ببريم
Well, how much are these white-bosomed slopes of Vermont ?
خب ول اين ته هاي ورمونت قدر ميشه؟
Twelve hundred !
هزار و دويست تا
Includes a nine-course, champagne thanksgiving dinner.
با نه تا راه شام قهرماني شکرزاري هم داريم
$1200 is a little rich for my blood, Harry.
هري، 1200تا براي آدمي مثل من يکمي زياده
Well, how short are you ?
قدر مي توني بدي؟
How short, Harry ?
قدر؟
So short it wouldn't be worth the trouble of you and George to measure.
اه خيلي تخفيف بدي براي تو و جرج نمي صرفه
- But, thanks for askin', all right ? - Mm-hmm.
بهر حال از يشنهادت ممنونم
- If you change your mind -- - What'd you do that for ? You know he's on aid.
اه نظرت عوض شد ه کار مي کني؟ تو که مي دوني ولي توي بساطش نيست
On major holidays, Willis, it's customary for the lord of the manor...
وليس توي يه همين تعطيلاتي رسمه که يه ارباب
- to offer drippings to the poor. - You're so full of shit !
به فقيرها يشنهاد بده تو ديوونه اي
- Hi. Mrs. Rossi ? - Yes ?
سلام خانم رزي؟ بله؟
I'm here about the weekend job.
من براي کار اومدم
Come on in.
بيا تو
Does he got pimples ? He hates pimples.
اون هم جوش روي صورتش داره؟ از يه آدم جوشي بدش مي ياد
Francine, be quiet.
فرانسين ساکت باش
Pimples. Pimples. Yeah.
جوشيه جوشي آره
Shush ! I'm sorry.
هيس متاسفم
- The school gave me your name, but I've forgotten it. - It's Charlie Simms.
مدرسه اسمتون رو بهم فته بود منتها فراموشش کردم ارلي سيمس
- How are you, Charlie ? - Fine, thanks.
طوري ارلي؟ خوبم ممنون
Right this way.
از اين طرف بيا
- You're available the whole weekend ? - Uh, yeah.
کل آخر هفته وقتت آزاده؟ بله
- Not going home for Thanksgiving ? - No.
براي مراسم شکرزاري نمي ري خونه؟ نه
[ Mrs. Rossi ] Good.
خوبه
They put him in a veteran's home, but he hated it,
اونها توي يه خونه دربه داغون ذاشتنش اما اون ازش متنفره
so I told my dad that we'd take him.
به درم فتم که يکي رو مي ياريم
Before you go in, do you mind my telling you a few things ?
قبل از اينکه بري اونجا بايد يه سري يزها رو برات توضيح بدم
Don't "sir" him and don't ask him too many questions.
بهش اصلا آقا و قربان نو ازش خيلي سوال نرس
And if he staggers a little when he gets up, don't pay any attention.
اه هم يه بار ديدي که لنيد و افتاد اصلا بهش توجهي نکن
[ Sigh ] Charlie, I can tell you're the right person for the job.
ارلي بايد بهت بم که تو فرد مناسبي براي اين کار هستي
and Uncle Frank's gonna like you a lot too.
عمو فرانک هک خيلي تعريفت رو کرده
Uh, where you gonna be this weekend ?
شما مي خواييد کجا بريد؟
We're driving to Albany.
به آلباني
Donny, my husband, has family there.
خانواده شوهرم، داني اونجاند
- Do you want Tommy in or out ? - [ Man ] Leave him out !
دوست داري تامي بيرون باشه يا بياد تو؟ بفرستش بيرون
He's chasin' that Calico ginch from the track houses again !
اون براش بيرون بهتره براي اينکه همش عادت داره دورو بر خونه رسه بزنه
Down deep, the man is a lump of sugar.
اصلا ناراحت نشو اينقدرها هم بداخلاق نيست
- Sir ? - Don't call me sir !
آقا؟ به من نو آقا
I-I'm sorry. I mean mister, sir.
متاسفم ببخشيد مي خواستم بم جناب
Uh-oh, we got a moron here, is that it ?
احمقم که اينجام درسته؟
No, mister -- Uh, that is --
نه آقا منظورم
Uh, Lieutenant. Yes, sir, Lieu--
ستوان بله قربان، ستوان
Lieutenant Colonel.
سرهن
26 years on the line, nobody ever busted me four grades before.
در 26سال خدمتم کسي نتونسته منو هار تادرجه ايين بياره
Get in here, you idiot !
بيا تو ببينم
Come a little closer. I wanna get a better look at ya.
بيا نزديکتر مي خوام بهتر ببينمت
How's your skin, son ?
وستت طوريه؟
My skin, sir ?
وستم قربان؟
- Oh, for Christ's sake. - I'm sorry, I don--
اوه تور و به خدابس کن متاسفم
Just call me Frank. Call me Mr. Slade.
منو فرانک صدا کن آقاي اسليد بهم بو
Call me Colonel, if you must. Just don't call me sir.
اه مي توني کلونل صدام کن فقط بهم نو آقا، قربان
All right, Colonel.
باشه کلونل
Simms, Charles. A senior.
سيمس، ارلز سيمس دانشجوي سال آخر
- You on student aid, Simms ? - Uh, yes, I am.
تو جز دانشجوهاي مستحق هستي، سيمس؟ بله درسته
For "student aid" read "crook."
براي بودن يه دانشجوي مستحق بايد کتاب کلاهبردار رو بخوني
Your father peddles car telephones at a 300% markup.
اونجا درت يه فروشنده دوره رد تلفنه
Your mother works on heavy commission in a camera store.
و مادرت هم متصدي فروش در يه فروشاه تجهيزات دوربين عکاسي ست
Graduated to it from espresso machines.
فارغ التحصيل دستاهاي قهوه جوش
What are you, dying of some wasting disease ?
خودت ي، از يه بيماري لاعلاج داري مي ميري؟
No, I'm right -- I'm right here.
نه ، من خوبم من الان اينجام
I know exactly where your body is.
خودم مي دونم دقيقا الان کجايي
What I'm lookin' for is some indication of a brain.
دنبال نشونه هايي از عقل و هوش در تو هستم
Too much football without a helmet ?
حتما فوتبال زياد بازي مي کني اون هم بدون کلاه ؟
Hah ! Lyndon's line on Gerry Ford.
خط ليندون در جري فورد
Deputy Debriefer, Paris Peace Talks, '68.
مامور شماره 68 اطلاعات اريس
Snagged the Silver Star and a silver bar. Threw me into G-2.
که به سيلور استار و بار سيلور برخورد مي کنه و من رو هم به طرف جي2 رت مي فرسته
G-2 ?
جي 2؟
Intelligence, of which you have none.
هوش و ذکاوت هموني که تو نداري
[ Yelling ] Where you from ?
اهل کجايي؟
Um, Gresham, Oregon,
رشهام ايالت ارون
s-- Colonel.
کلونل
What does your daddy do in Gresham, Oregon ?
درت در رشهام ارون ه کاره ست؟
Hmm ? Count wood chips ?
هان؟ شاخه درختها رو مي شمره؟
Uh, my stepfather and my mom run a convenience store.
خب نادري و مادرم يه مجتمع رفاهي رو اداره مي کنند
- How convenient ! What time they open ? - 5:00 A.M.
مجتمع رفاهي!جالبه، ساعت ند بازش مي کنند؟ 5صبح
- Close ? - 1:00 A.M.
کي مي بندند؟ 1نصف شب
Hard workers.
خيلي سخت کوشند
You got me all misty-eyed !
تو باعث مي شي شمهام تار بشند
So, what are you doin' here in this sparrow-fart town ?
توي اين شهر وامونده ه کار مي کني؟
I, l-- I attend Baird.
من،من در بيرد هستم
Attend Baird !
در بيرد
I know you go to the Baird school.
مي دونم در مدرسه بيرد هستي
Point is, how do you afford it,
مسئله اينجاست که طوري تونستي
even with the student aid and the folks back home hustlin' corn nuts ?
با وجو بودن يه دانشجوي محتاج و اون والدين سخت کوشت توي اين مدرسه درس بخوني؟
[ Sigh ] I won a, uh, Young America merit scholarship.
تونستم کمک هزينه دانشجويي جوانان آمريکا رو بيرم
§ Glory, glory Hallelujah §
ه افتخارآميز، واقعا جاي افتخار داره بايد شکر خدا کرد
- [ Knocking ] - Who's there ?
کي اونجاست؟
- That little piece of tail ?
مارمولک کوولو؟
Get her outta here !
از اينجا م شو و برو
Yeah.
آره
Can't believe they're my blood.
نمي شه باور کرد که اونها از خون منند
I.Q. of sloths and the manners of banshees.
وهوششون به اون تنبل و تن رور رفته IQ
He's a mechanic, she's a homemaker.
درشون مکانيکه مادرشون هم خونه دار
He knows as much about cars as a beauty queen,
به اندازه ملکه زيبايي در مورد ماشين مطلب مي دونه
and she bakes cookies, taste like wing nuts.
و زنش هم فقط بلده کيک بزه و توش يزهاي جوواجور بريزه
As for the tots, they're twits.
از دست اون دوتا دوتا به ها هم دوقلوند
How's your skin, son ? I like my aides to be presentable.
وستت ه طوريه، سر؟ نمي خوام از کمک کردن بهت دريغ کنم
Well, I -- I've had a few zits.
خب من يکم روي صورتم جوش داشتم
Um, but my roommate, he lent me his Clinique because he's from --
اما همکلاسي ام به من آدرس کلينيکي که خودش مي رفت رو بهم داد آخه اون اهل
"The History of My Skin," by Charles Simms.
"سرذشت وست من" اثر ارلز سيمس
You patronizing me, peewee ? Hmm ?
تو داري منو تشويق به حرف زدن مي کني؟ هان؟
You givin' me that old prep school palaver ?
مي خواي که برات بشينم و از اون دبستان وراجي کنم؟
Baird School !
مدرسه بيرد
A bunch of runny-nosed snots in tweed jackets...
يه مشت دماغ آويزون ژاکت وشند که
all studyin' to be George Bush.
تمام تلاششون اينه که جرج بوش بشند
Well...
خب
I believe President Bush went to Andover, Colonel.
کلونل فکر کنم که رئيس جمهور بوش به مدرسه آندور رفتند
You sharpshootin' me, punk ?
داري منو دست مي اندازي؟
Is that what you're doin' ?
مي خواي مسخره ام کني؟
Don't you sharpshoot me !
حق نداري منو دست بندازي
You'll give me forty.
من بهت هل تا مي دم
Then you're gonna give me forty more.
بعدش تو ازمن بيشتر از هل تا مي خواي
Then you're gonna pull K.P., the grease pit !
بعد اون هم ديه راضي نمي شي من هم مي دونم باهات ه کار کنم
I'll rub your nose in enlisted men's crud...
بلايي به سرت مي يارم که هي وقت نفهمي از کجا خوردي
till you don't know which end is up ! You understand ?
و هي وقت هم برات اين نحسي تمومي نداشته باشه شيرفهم شد؟
Yeah.
بله
- What do you want ? - What do you mean, what do I want ?
ي مي خواي؟ منظورتون يه که ي مي خوام؟
What do you want here ?
اينجا دنبال ي هستي؟
I wa-want a job.
کار
Yeah, I want a job so I can make, you know,
بله همونطور که  مي دونيد من به يه کار نياز دارم
my plane fare home for Christmas.
تا بتونم کرايه سفرم رو براي کريسمس در بيارم
God, you're touching !
خداي من تو آدمو ناراحت مي کني
Still here, poormouth ?
هنوز اينجايي به؟
Convenience store... my ass !
مجتمع رفاهي فکر مي کني من احمقم
Hustlin' jalapeno dips to the appleseeds.
که خيلي سخت کوشند و توي کارشون غرق شدند
Go on.
برو
Dismissed.
مرخصي
- [ Children Chattering ] - [ Charlie ] Mrs. Rossi ?
خانم رسي؟
Charlie, we're up here ! Come on up.
ارلي ما اينجاييم بيا بالا
- Uh, this is Donny. - Hey, Charlie.
اين داني سلام ارلي
Hi.
سلام
Uh, Mrs. Rossi, I got the feelin' I screwed up.
خانم رسي فکر کنم که نتونستم اين کار رو بيرم
- Oh, you couldn't have. - It was a bad interview.
نتونستي مصاحبه جالبي نبود
That was no interview, Charlie. You're it.
ارلي اين اصلا مصاحبه نبود تو الان سرکاري
You're the only one that showed up. You have to take the job.
تو تنها کسي هستي که براي اين کار اومدي و تونستي اين کار رو بيري
He sleeps a lot. You can watch television, call your girlfriend.
اون زياد مي خوابه مي توني تلويزيون تماشا کني و به دوست دخترت هم زن بزني
I promise you, an easy 300 bucks.
بهت قول مي دم که 300تا رو مي توني در بياري
[ Sigh ] I don't get an easy feeling.
ولي کار آسوني نيست
His bark is worse than his bite.
اون فقط هارت و هورت داره
He was a great soldier, a real hero.
يه سرباز بزري بوده يه قهرمان
The man grows on you !
ازش خوشت مي ياد
By Sunday night, you'll be best friends.
بهت قول مي دم تا يکشنبه شب دوستهاي خوبي براي هم مي شيد
[ Sigh ] Charlie, please.
ارلي خواهش مي کنم
I want to get away for a few days, and Uncle Frank won't come with us.
مي خوام يه ند روزي از اينجا برم و عمو فرانک با ما نمي ياد
Six months ago, he could sometimes tell light from dark,
شش ماه يش اون وضعش خيلي بهتر بود مي يومد بيرون
but now there's nothing.
اما الان هي تعريفي نداره
I feel better having someone else around just in case.
فکر نکنم  کس ديه اي بياد و اين کار رو بيره
Please ?
خواهش مي کنم؟
Okay, Mrs. Rossi. Sure.
باشه خانم رسي باشه
- [ Sigh ] Thank you, Charlie. - Come here, you.
ممنونم ارلي بفرماييد
There you go.
ممنونم
[ George ] Chas ! Chas, hold up !
ارلي ارلي وايستا
- How ya doin' ? - I'm good.
طوري؟ خوبم
That's great.
عاليه
This can't go out. This is on reserve.
نمي توني ببريش بيرون اين مرجع شده
Here's the thing.
خب فقط يدونه ست
I need the book tonight...
من امشب به کتابي احتياج دارم
- for a Thanksgiving quiz with big-shit Preston in the morning. - Yeah, I know.
که آيين مراسم شکرزاري ترسون رو داشته باشه آره مي دونم
That's why he put it on reserve. This is our only copy.
اما اين کتاب فقط يک نسخه ست حق بيرون بردنش رو نداري
Chas, I'm pullin' an all-nighter.
ارلي تمام شب دنبالش بودم
Without that book I'm dead, okay ?
بدون اين من مي ميرم ،رضايت بده ديه؟
If it's not back by 7:30, it's gonna be my ass.
اه تا ساعت 7:30 صبح برنرده از من جواب مي خواند
Oh, I promise. I promise.
قول مي دم قول
- [ Whispering ] Got it ? - Yeah.
رفتيش؟ آره
Just a second. I gotta lock up.
فقط يه ثانيه بزار در رو قفل کنم
Okay.
باشه
God, can you wait to get out of this dump or what ?
مي توني يه دقيق صبر کني ببينم ي کار بايد با اين لعنتي بکنم؟
Where you guys going skiing again ?
براي اسکي مي خواييد کجا بريد؟
- Sugarloaf or -- - It's bush, Chas, Sugarbush.
شورلاف يا اونجا اسم يه جنله ارلز، شوربراش
That's my boys. [ Whistles ] What are you doin' ?
به ها رو ناه کن ي کار مي کنيد؟
Keep your voice down !
صدات رو بيار ايين
I'll tell you about it in the morning.
صبح برات تعريف مي کنم
- Shh. - Wha--
هيس ي
- Miss Hunsaker, have a nice day ? - George, why all the noise ?
خانم هانسکير، ه روز خوبيه درسته؟ جرج اين سرو صداها براي يه؟
[ Whispering ] It's hunsaker ! Go ! Go !
هانسکير، بدو بدو برو
I was just messin' around with Chas.
اينجا با ارلز وايستاده بودم مي زديم
- Good evening, Charles. - Hi, Mrs. Hunsaker.
شب بخير ارلز سلام خانم هانسکير
- What was that ? - I don't know, ma'am.
ي بود؟ نمي دونم خانم
- Who were those boys ? What were they doing ? - Oh, who knows ?
اون سرها کي بودند؟ ي کار مي کردند؟ اوه کسي ه مي دونه؟
- Charles ? - Um --
ارلز؟
- Did you make this scarf yourself ? - No, George, I bought it.
اين شال رو خودتون بافتيد؟ نه جرج خريدمش
- 'Cause it's a beauty. It really is. - Thank you, George.
آخه ديدم خيلي قشنه ممونم جرج
In case I don't see you before the Thanksgiving holidays,
بهر حال شما منو قبل از مراسم شکرزاري ديديد درسته؟
- why don't you give me one of your big hugs ? - Oh, George !
خب را براي تبريک بغلم نمي کنيد هان؟ اوه جرج
- Please ? Come on. - Good evening, boys.
خواهش مي کنم زود باشيد شب بخير سرها
Good-bye, Mrs. Hunsaker.
خداحافظ خانم هانسکير
[ Jimmy On Loudspeaker ] Mr. Trask is our fearless leader,
آقاي ترسک يک مدير بي باک و نترسي ست
a man of learning, a voracious reader.
مردي دانشمند با ولع زياد براي خواندن
He could recite the "Iliad" in ancient greek...
درحال ماهييري قزل آلا در رودهاي خروشان
while fishing for trout in a rippling creek.
مي تواند کتابهاي ادبيات باستان يونان را بخواند
Endowed with wisdom, of judgement sound,
فردي سخاوتمند و خردمند داراي صداي عدالت ونه
nevertheless about him the questions abound.
هياه رسش سوالي از ايشان بي اسخ نمي ماند
How does Mr. Trask make such wonderful deals ?
نظرتان راجع به اظهار نظرات در مورد آقاي ترسک يست؟
Why did the trustees buy him Jaguar wheels ?
را از هيات امنا رخ براي ماشين ايشان تهيه نمي کنيد؟
He wasn't conniving !
وي اهل شم وشي نيست
He wasn't crass !
کودن و احمق هم نيست
He merely puckered his lips...
فقط لبهاش رو جمع مي کنه
- and kissed their ass ! - [ Boys Laughing ]
و به رخهاي قراضه بوسه مي زنه
Come on.
زودباش
One more ! One more, come on !
يکم ديه ، يالا زودباش ديه
Fuck you !
!لعنتي
[ Trask ] Mr. Simms, Mr. Willis.
آقاي سيمس و آقاي ويليس
Mrs. Hunsaker says that you gentlemen were at a vantage point last night...
خانم هانسکير مي ند که شما دو نفر ديديد که ه افردي بودند
to observe who was responsible for this, uh,
ون شما فقط ديشب فرصت داشتيد تا ببينيد که اون کار کيه
stunt.
همون شيرين کاري
Who was it ?
کار کي بود؟
I really couldn't tell you, sir.
واقعا نمي تونم بهتون بم
Um, I thought I saw someone fooling with the lamppost,
فقط مي تونم بم که يکي بالاي تير راغ برق بوده
but by the time I pulled focus, they were gone.
تا اومدم دقت کنم که کيا هستند، رفته بودند
Mr. Simms ?
آقاي سيمس؟
I couldn't say.
نمي تونم بم، نديدم
That automobile is not just a possession of mine.
اون ماشين مال خودن نيست
That automobile was presented to me by the Board of Trustees.
از طرف هيات امنا بهم داده شده
It is a symbol of the standard of excellence for which this school is known,
نماد و سمبل الوي برتري و ممتاز بودن مدرسه ست که همه مدرسه رو با همين مي شناسند
and I will not have it tarnished.
و من هم تا به حال اونو کثيف نکرده بودم
The automobile ?
ماشين؟
The standard, Mr. Willis.
نماد و الو آقاي ويليس
- What's your position, Mr. Simms ? - On what, sir ?
وظيفه شما يه اقاي سيمس؟ در مورد ي قربان؟
On preserving the reputation of Baird.
در حفظ و نهداري شهرت مدرسه بيرد
- I-I'm for Baird. - Then, who did it ?
خب من براي بيرد کار مي کنم خب بو کار کي بود؟
I really couldn't say for sure.
مطمئن باشيد نمي دونم
Very well.
بسيار خب
First thing Monday, I'm convening a special session...
اولين کاري که بايد بکنم اينه که دوشنبه يه جلسه اي با
of the student-faculty disciplinary committee.
کميته انضباطي دانشجويان تشکيل بدم
As this is a matter which concerns the whole school,
در مورد کل مدرسه بايد در اون جلسه صحبت بشه
the entire student body will be present.
کل دانشجويان بايد حاضر باشند
There will be no classes, no activities.
هي کلاسي هم تشکيل نمي شه
Nothing will transpire at this institution...
هي يزي هم از اينجا بيرون درز يدا نمي کنه
until that proceeding is concluded.
تا به نتيجه برسيم
And if, at that time, we are no further along than we are now,
و اه تا اون موقع من يزي از تصميمم بشنوم
I will expel you both.
جفتتون رو اخراج مي کنم
Mr. Willis, would you excuse us ?
آقاي ويليس بايد ما رو ببخشيد؟
Have a nice Thanksgiving.
مراسم شکرزاري خوبي داشته باشيد
Thank you. You too, Mr. Willis.
ممنون شما هم همين طور آقاي ويليس
I will.
حتما
Mr. Simms.
آقاي سيمس
I'm not quite through with you yet.
من هنوز نمي دونم اين موضوع به تو ارتباط داره يا نه
One of the few perks of this office is that...
موضوعي که الان توي اين برحه زماني مهمه
I am empowered to handle certain matters on my own as I see fit.
اينه که من قدرت انجام هر کاري رو که صلاح بدونم دارم
Do you understand ?
متوجه که مي شي؟
- Yes, sir. - Good.
بله قربان خوبه
The Dean of Admissions at Harvard and I have an arrangement.
رئيس دانشاه هاروارد هر سال ليستي به ما مي فرسته
Along with the usual sheaf of applicants submitted by Baird,
تا دانشجويان مستعد رو براي ادامه تحصيل به اونها معرفي کنيم
of which virtually,
دانشجويان واقعا مستعد
oh, two-thirds are guaranteed admittance,
اجازه معرفي دوسوم دانشجويان رو داريم
I add one name,
و من هم مي تونم يک اسم اضافه کنم
somebody who's a standout and yet, underprivileged;
کسي که دانشجوي محروم بي بضاعتي باشه
a student who cannot afford to pay the board and tuition in Cambridge.
که نتونه شهريه تحصيلش رو بده
Do you know on whose behalf I drafted a memo this year ?
مي دوني اسم ه کسي رو امسال توي يش نويسش نوشتم؟
- No, sir. - You. You, Mr. Simms.
نه قربان تو ، تو آقاي سيمس
Now can you tell me who did it ?
حالا مي توني بي کار کي بوده؟
No, sir, I can't.
نه قربان نمي تونم
You take the weekend to think about it, Mr. Simms.
آقاي سيمس تا آخر هفته وقت داري که خوب فکر کني
Good afternoon.
عصر بخير
What'd he say ?
ي مي فت؟
- Nothin'. - What do you mean, nothing ?
هيي منظورت يه، هيي؟
He said the same thing. He just said it over.
همون يزها رو فقط با آب و تاب بيشتر
You know what he's doing ?
مي دوني مي خواد ه کار کنه؟
He's good-cop, bad-coppin' us.
اون يه ليس خوبيه ما هم سربازهاي بد
He knows I'm old guard. You're fringe.
اون مي دونه که من يه سرباز قديمي ام و تو يه سرباز تازه کار
He's gonna bear down on me and soft-soap you.
مجبوره که منو تحمل کنه و با تو با نرمي و ملايمت صحبت کنه
[ Laughing ] Did he try to soft-soap you ? Did he ?
حالا بو اين کار رو کرد يا نه؟
No.
نه
Chas, I detect a slight panic pulse from you. Are you panicking ?
ارلز متوجه شدم که قدر ترسيدي درسته ترسيدي؟
- Yeah, a little. - Come on.
آره يکمي بيا
- You're on scholarship, right ? - Yeah.
تو کمک هزينه دانشجويي مي يري؟ آره
You're on scholarship from Oregon... at Baird.
تو از ارون کمک هزينه دانشجويي مدرسه بيرد رو مي يري
You're a long way from home, Chas.
ارلز تو خونتون تا اينجا خيلي دوره
What's that got to do with anything ?
خب اين ه ربطي داره؟
I don't know how it works out there.
من هم نمي دونم نتيجه ي ميشه
But how it works here ? We stick together.
اما نتيجه هر ي که بشه مهم اينه که ما باهميم
It's us against them, no matter what.
مسئله همينه که ما مقابل اونها هستيم
We don't cover our ass. We don't tell our parents.
روي حماقتمون سروش نمي ذاريم به در و مادرمون هم نمي يم
Stonewall everybody !
مثل کوه وايمستيم
And above all, never, never...
علاوه براون هي وقت هي وقت
Leave any of us twisting in the wind.
خودمون رو نبايد ببيازيم
And that's it.
فقط همين
What does that have to do with me being on scholarship ?
را رسيدي که کمک هزينه مي يرم؟
I'm just tryin' to bring you up to speed, kid, that's it.
فقط مي خواستم بهت بم که درست رو سريعتر بخوني
Thanks.
ممنون
I'll tell you what. Give me a few hours to figure out the moves,
مي خوام يه يزي بهت بم ند ساعت بهم فرصت بده تا بفهمم اوضاع طوره
and call me tonight in Vermont.
بعدش به من در ورمونت تلفن بزن
I'll be at the Sugarbush lodge, all right ?
من ميرم شوربراش باشه؟
All right.
باشه
You all right ?
با توام؟
Yeah, I guess so.
باشه فکر مي کنم
Okay.
خوبه
Try to keep him down to four drinks a day.
نزار بيشتر از هار بار در روز مشروب بخوره
If you can keep him down to forty, you're doin' good.
اه تا هل بار هم نتونستي اصلا خودت رو ناراحت نکن کارت رو خوب انجام دادي
Try to water them down a little. Do you know how to do that ?
مي توني جاش آب بهش بدي مي دوني که طوري بايد انجام بدي؟
- It's a long ride, honey ! - Get the bags in the car. I'll be right out.
عزيزم سفر طولانيه مدونها رو بزار توي ماشين من هم الان مي يام
Mommy, Mommy ! Don't forget Uncle Frank's walk.
مامان مامان ياده روي عمو فرانک يادت نره
[ Mrs. Rossi ] Oh, ha... Yeah.
آره راست مي ه
Uh, you have to air him out...
در روز هم يکمي
a little every day.
ببرش بيرون هواخوري
Why don't you go on back there, get yourself oriented ?
را نمي ري اونجا ببيني اوضاع طوريه؟
I'll come out in a minute, give you telephone numbers and stuff.
يه دقيقه ديه بر مي ردم تا شماره تلفن بهت بدم
[ Frank ] Well, I wouldn't try a thing like that...
خب من اصلا نمي خواستم که
unless I knew, would I ?
اه مي دونستم مي تونستم؟
Just let me speak to her.
بزار باهاش صحبت کنم
Hello, beautiful. Is that you ?
سلام زيباي من خودتي؟
Yeah, we spoke yesterday.
آره ما ديروز صحبت کرديم
[ Chuckling ] You have a glass of wine with lunch ?
يه يلاس مشروب با ناهارت خوردي؟
You sound a little dusky. Hmm.
صدات هم يکمي رفته بود
- [ Clearing Throat ] - Just a minute, sweetheart.
يه لحظه وشي عزيزم
You're back, huh ?
برشتي آره؟
Tenacious !
آدم سرسختي هستي
Get out my dress blues. They're in a garment bag in the closet.
لباسهاي آبي منو از توي نجه لباسها در بيار
Check the top dresser drawer. Take out the shoulder boards...
خوب روبروي دراور بزارشون و سرشونه هاشون رو درست کن
and affix them shoulders right and left,
و هر کدوم رو سر جاي خودشون بذار
A.S.A.P. That means now.
اين اولين درسه شروع کن
Hello.
الو
Sorry to keep you waitin', sweetheart.
ببخشيد از اينکه منتظرت ذاشتم عزيزم
I'm not the kind of guy who likes to rush things,
من از اون مردهايي نيستم که با عجله کار کنم
but I'm catchin' a 4:00 at Logan, lookin' out my window, and there's not a taxi in sight.
اما من ساعت 4 به لوان رسيدم، از نجره ناه کردم،تاکسي نديدم
What happened to Chet ?
براي ت ه اتفاقي افتاد؟
He didn't invest in a radio yet ?
هنوز نتونسته توي راديو سرمايه ذاري کنه؟
Hah ! Well, get your driver on it.
خب به رانندت بو
Tell him to get a move on.
بهش بو که حرکت کنه
Yes. Mmm.
آره درسته
Some kind of body has got to go with that bedroom voice.
مثل اينکه صداي يکي از توي اتاق خواب مي ياد
One day I'm gonna swing by, get a better look at it.
يه روزي مي يام و مي رقصم تو هم بهش بيشتر دقت کن
You bet.
باهات شرط مي بندم
Bye.
خداحافظ
My val-pak's underneath the bed. Get it out.
ژاکت و وليورم هم زير تخته بيارشون بيرون
Put the boards on the blues and fold 'em in.
خوب و مرتب کنار اون لباس آبي ها تاشون کن
Uh, are we going someplace, Colonel ?
کلونل ما قراره جايي بريم؟
What business is that of yours ? Don't shrug, imbecile.
خب کارت يه؟ شونه هات رو هم بالا ننداز
I'm blind. Save your body language for the bimbi.
من کور هستم اما حرکات بدنت رو خوب متوجه مي شم
- Now, get my gear out. - Francine, get in the car.
حالا لباسهام رو بيار بيرون فرانسين بيا تو ماشين
It's almost 3:00. The goddamn Flintstones haven't left yet.
ساعت 3 بايد باشه صداشون بازم مي ياد مه نرفتند
[ Mr. Rossi ] Willie Rossi must go in the car !
ويلي روسي بايد بري توي ماشين
- Here comes Mrs. Rossi now. - Damn it !
خانم روسي دارند مي ياند اينجا لعنتي
She said good-bye to me three times today.
امروز سه بار تا به حال با من خداحافظي کرده
What's she got, separation anxiety ?
ه شه نمي دونم حتما از دوري من هيجانزده ست؟
Cut her off at the door !
نزار بياد توي خونه
Hi, honey. Bye, honey.
سلام عزيزم خداحافظ عزيزم
I wish you were coming with us.
ايکاش شما هم با ما مي اومدين
Me too.
من هم دوست داشتم
Maybe next time.
شايد دفعه ديه بيام
- Drive carefully now. - Yeah.
با احتياط رانندي کنيد باشه
Charlie, this is where we'll be.
ارلي اين تلفن اونجايي که ما هستيم
Good luck, Charlie. Don't let him drink too much.
موفق باشي نذار فقط خيلي مشروب بخوره
See ya, Charlie !
به اميد ديدار ارلي
And no 900 numbers. He loves to talk dirty.
براي هزارمين بار بهت مي م نذار زياده روي کنه
All right, let's get to work.
خب حالا بيا سر کارت
L-buckles givin' you trouble ?
سک مدون اذيتت مي کنه؟
Never in the Boy Scouts, sluggo ?
تا به حال يش آهن بودي؟
- I, I made Tenderfoot. - Tenderfoot, my foot !
بله يش آهني کردم البته خيلي ابتدايي ابتدايي
Convenience-store mama's boy.
اي سر ماماني والدين مجتمع رفاهي
Here. Let me take a look at that.
بياييد اينجا رو بيريد
Touch me again, I'll kill ya, you little son-of-a-bitch !
اه يه دفعه ديه به من دست بزني روزارت رو سياه مي کنم
I touch you. Understand ?
من به تو دست مي زنم شيرفهم شد؟
My shoulder boards are in the top dresser drawer. Get them, son.
سردوشي هاي من توي کشو بالايي هست بيارشون
The epaulets with the silver oak leaf.
شکل بر بلوطند و رنشون هم نقره ايه
- Are these -- - Good.
ايناند آره
Taxi come yet ?
هنوز تاکسي نيومده؟
Colonel, where are we going ?
کلنل ما کجا ميريم؟
Where we going ?
کجا مي ريم؟
Freak show central.
مرکز نمايش عجايب
- Where's that ? - New York City.
کجاست؟ نيويورک
That's in New York, son. New York State.
نيويورک سر شهر نيويورک
Uh, Mrs. Rossi didn't say anything to me about going anywhere.
آخه خانم روسي يزي بهم در مورد رفتن نفت
She forgot.
فراموشش شد
- Should we call her, 'cause I -- - You kidding me ?
بايد بهش بيم که داريم مي ريم، آخه من منو دست انداختي؟
Call her ? By the time they get to Albany in that "hupmobile" he drives...
مي خواي باهاش تماس بيري؟ اونجوري که اون به سمت آلباني رانندي مي کنه
it'll be opening day at Saratoga.
تا فردا به ساراتوا مي رسند
- Colonel, I can't go to New York City. - Why not ?
کلنل من نمي تونم به نيويورک برم؟ را ؟
New York --
نيويورک
- New York's too much responsibility. - Ah, responsibility !
نيويورک شهر شلوغيه، آدم خيلي بايد مواظب خودش باشه ها شلوغ؟
I had a lot of 17 year olds my first platoon.
من بيشتر از 17سال توي نيويورک مسئوليت اولين روه جوخه افراد خودم رو داشتم
I took care of them. All set !
مراقب همشون هم بودم خب ديه ي؟
How do I look ?
تيم طوره؟
Tickets. Money.
بليط.ول
Speech.
نطق
Old Washington joke... from my days with Lyndon.
و يه جک قديمي واشينتوني از زمانهايي که با ليندم بودم هم با خودم دارم
-[ Honking ] -I knew I could count on transportation.
بايد انتظار بارکشي رو مي داشتم
Are you ready ?
خب حاضري؟
This is not Panmunjom. A simple yes will do.
اصلا کار شاقي نيست فقط کافيه بي بله و شم
- Um -- - Good ! Here you go.
خوبه بريم
Come on ! Hup to it, son !
بيا سر بجنب
You're in front of me. Let's go.
بيافت جلوي من برو
- [ Meowing ] - [ Frank ] Tomster, come here, boy.
تامستر، بيا سر
Psst, psst. Come on.
بيا اينجا
Here, tomster, come on. Tomster, tomster. Yeah.
اينجا تامستر بيا آهان آفرين
Remember, when in doubt... fuck.
يادت باشه که هرکاري که خواستي بکن
Good afternoon, sir. Where's our destination ?
عصربخير آقا مقصدتون کجاست؟
Our destination... New York City, home of the brave !
مقصدمون شهر نيويورکه خونه به هاي شجاع و نترس
- Two for the shuttle to New York. - I'm not shuttling anywhere.
دو تا بليط قطار نيويورک من تا به حال با قطار جايي نرفتم
- Look at those tickets. "First class." - Yes, sir, first class.
به اين بليط ها ناه کن، درجه يکه بله درسته درجه يکه
You bought me a ticket ? I never said I'd go to New York.
شما براي من هم بليط خريديد؟ من که فتم نيويورک نمي يام
What are you, some kind of chicken-shit, sticks to job description only ?
ت شده تا کي مي خواي به اون کارهاي مزخرف ادامه بدي؟
Gate 46, sir.
درب 46قربان
- As you were, son. - Thank you, sir.
اين هم مال تو سر ممنونم قربان
Which way's the door ?
در از کدوم طرفه؟
- Are you blind ? Are you blind ? - Of course not.
مه کوري؟ نمي بيني؟ البته که نيستم
Then why do you keep grabbin' my goddamn arm ?
س را عين کورها دستم رو مي يري؟
I take your arm.
من دست تو رو مي يرم
- I'm sorry. - Don't be sorry.
متاسفم عذرخواهي نکن
How would you know, watchin' MTV all your life ?
مي دوني طوري مي توني در طول عمرت برنامه هاي ام تي وي رو ببيني؟
Yes !
عاليه
- Jack Daniels... - You bet.
جک دانيلز شرط مي بندم خودشه
- And Diet Slice. - The old Diet Slice.
و دايت اسلايز دايت اسلايز مونده و کهنه
- And a water. - Thank you, Daphne.
و آب ممنونم دافنه
Certainly, sir.
خواهش مي کنم آقا
How did you know her name ?
از کجا اسمش رو مي دونيد؟
Well, she's wearin' Floris.
خب مثل ل فروشها لباس وشيده بود
That's an English cologne.
لباس قديمي انليسي
But her voice is California chickie.
اما صداش شبيه رنده هاي کاليفرنيايي بود
Now, California chickie bucking for English lady --
مي دوني که اون رنده ها هم با خانمهاي انليسي خوب نيستند
I call her Daphne.
به خاطر همين بهش مي م دافنه
Oh, big things may happen to that little thing of yours.
را يه يز اينقدر کويک تو رو ناراحت کرده
Look, Colonel,
ببينيد کلنل
- I'll get you to New York, all right ? - Uh-huh.
من دارم شما رو مي برم نيويورک درسته؟
Then I'm gonna have to turn around and come back.
بعدش هم بايد وقتي کارم که تموم شد برردم
Well, Chuck, you gotta do what you gotta do.
خب اک،تو اون کاري رو که بايد انجام بدي، مي دي
Charlie, all right ? Or Charles.
ارلي بيد باشه؟ يا ارلز
Sorry. I can't blame you, though.
متاسفم بهر حال من که نمي خوام تو رو با اين اسم کويک کنم
Chuck is a --
اک يعني
So, why are we going to New York ?
اصلا را مي خواييد بريد نيويورک؟
All information will be given on a need-to-know basis.
اطلاعات دقيق رو هر وقت که لازم شد بهت مي دم
Whoo-ah !
دافنه کجاست؟ صداش کن بياد اينجا
She's in the back.
اون شته
A tail's in the tail.
خودش نيست اثرش که هست
Oh, but I still smell her. [ Sniffing ]
اما من بوش رو حس مي کنم
Women !
بوي زن
What can you say ?
نظرت يه؟
Who made 'em ?
کي اونها رو خلق کرده؟
God must have been a fuckin' genius.
خدا حتما خودش با اين موجودات بااستعداد خوش ذرونده
The hair --
موهاشون
They say the hair is everything, you know.
مي دوني مي ند که مو همه يزه
Have you ever buried your nose in a mountain of curls...
تا به حال بيني ات رو توي ي و تابهاي موهاشون بردي
and just wanted to go to sleep forever ?
و بخواي تا ابد به خواب بري؟
Or lips --
...يا لب هاشون
and when they touched, yours were like...
،و وقتي تماس برقرار بشه ...مال تو مثل
that first swallow of wine...
...اولين جرعه شراب
after you just crossed the desert.
.بعد از عبور از بيابان هستن
Tits ! Whoo-ah !
!سينه ها
Big ones, little ones,
،کويک هاشون، بزر هاشون
nipples staring right out at ya...
...نوکشون درست بهت زل ميزنن
Like secret searchlights.
.مثل نورافکن هاي مخفي
And legs --
...و اهاشون
I don't care if they're Greek columns...
برام مهم نيست ...ستون هاي يوناني باشه
or secondhand Steinways.
.يا دست دوم هاي استين وي
What's between 'em,
،يزي که بينشون هست
passport to heaven.
،اسورت به بهشت
I need a drink.
بايد يه يزي بخورم
Yes, Mr. Simms,
خب آقاي سيمسز
there's only two syllables in this whole wide world worth hearing:
فقط دو کلمه وجود دارند که توي اين دنيا تلفظ مي شند و اون هم
pussy.
بدن زنه
Are you listening to me, son ? I'm givin' you pearls here.
وشت با منه؟ حرفهاي ارزشمندي برات مي م
I guess you really like women.
فکر کنم شما واقعا زنها رو دوست داريد
Oh, above all things !
اوه البته بيشتر از هر يزي
A very, very distant second...
و بعد اون يزي که در درجه هاي بعدي قرار داره
is a Ferrari.
ماشين فراري هست
Charlie ?
ارلي؟
Give me your hand.
دستت رو بده به من
This is just the start of your education, son.
اين اولين درس توست سر
- Where are we ? - Where are we, eh ?
ما کجاييم؟ کجاييم هان؟
The cynosure of all things civilized:
سناتوري و مجلس متمدن ها
the Waldorf-Astoria.
والدورف استريا
The last time I was here, Charlie, was with a G-2 from Brussels.
آخرين باري که اينجا بودم به خاطر جلسه جي 2 بروکسل بود
Had a Ferrari.
اون موقع يه فراري داشتم
Every day I held the door open for the fucker.
هر روز در ماشين رو براي فاحشه ها باز مي کردم
Never even offered me a ride.
هي وقت هم کسي به من يشنهادي نمي داد
Well, fuck him.
بالاخره هم يه روزي دخل ماشن رو آوردم
He's dead and I'm blind.
اون از بين رفت و من هم کور شدم
- Spread the word. - Thank you, sir.
اين يغام رو برو و برسون ممنونم قربان
- The intelligence will be forthcoming ? - Sir ?
روش جاسوسي شماها  يشرفت کرده؟ ببخشيد متوجه نشدم؟
On the escort scene.
منظورم کيوسک نهبانيه
Um, yes, sir.
بله قربان متوجه شدم
- And welcome to the Waldorf. - Gracias, amigo.
درضمن به والدرف خوش اومديد
Puerto Ricans... always made the best infantrymen.
يترو ريکانز هميشه بهترين سربازهاي ياده نظام رو آماده مي کرد
I'm home again.
خوبه دوباره توي خونه ام هستم
Give me an inventory on this, will you ?
يه فهرستي از يزهايي که اونجاست، مي توني بهم بدي؟
All right, where am l, in Asia ?
خب من کجام توي قاره آسيا؟
He told me the phone was on the other side of the room, didn't he ?
اون بهم فت که تلفن طرف ديه اتاق هست، درسته؟
By the windows ?
کنار نجره؟
It's right here.
ايناهاش اينجاست
Okay.
خوبه
We're in business.
کارمون رو شروع مي کنيم
Get me the Oak Room.
سالن بلوط رو برام بيريد
How's that inventory comin' ?
ي شد فهرست رو بهم فتي يا نه؟
Uh, there's Jim Beam and Early Times.
يه دونه جيم بيم و يکي هم ارلي تايمز هست
Quartermaster's on the take again. Hello.
متصدي رو دوباره برام بير الو
Is Sheldon or Mack there ?
مارک شلدن يا ماک هست يا نه؟
This is Lt. Col. Frank Slade.
من کلنل فرانک اسليد هستم
I used to be a regular. I used to come in with a General Garbisch.
من عادت دارم که منظم باشم و هميشه دلم مي خواد نوشيدني ام رو با مارم اربي شروع کنم
Yes, that's probably because he's at Arlington six feet under.
بله، حتما براي اينکه آرلينتون شش قدم ايين تره
Listen up. I want a table for two, and I don't mean Siberia, 8:15.
خوب وش کنيد. من يه ميز دو نفره مي خوام نمي خوام فکر کنم که توي سيبري ام، ساعت8:15
Clear them little bottles off.
بطري هاي کويک رو تمييز کنيد
And when I get off the phone, call up Hyman.
وقتي تلفن رو قطع کردم هايمن رو صدا کنيد
Tell him I want it wall to wall with John Daniels.
بهش بيد مي خوام ديوار به ديوار جان دانيلز باشم
Uh, don't you mean, uh, Jack Daniels ?
منظورتون که جک دانيلز که نيست؟
He may be Jack to you, son. But when you've known him as long as I have --
شايد براي تو جک باشه اما وقتي ببينيش مي فهمي
That's a joke. Hello !
که اين همش يه جک هست الو
This is Lt. Col. Frank Slade. I would like a limo, 8:00.
کلنل فرانک اسليد هستم راس ساعت 8شراب با مارک ليمو برام بياريد
What are you drinkin' ?
نوشيدني مي خوري؟
Uh, nothing, thanks. I don't use it.
نه ممنونم عادت ندارم
What's useful about it ?
فايده هاشو نمي دوني؟
I don't know. Listen, Colonel, I have to get going.
نه نمي دونم کلنل، ببينيد من مي خوام برردم
Where you goin' ?
کجا برردي؟
Back to school. I've got some real important stuff I have to take care of.
به مدرسه من کارهاي مهمتري هم دارم که بايد انجامشون بدم
Very well.
بسيار خب
But I never let my aides leave on an empty stomach.
اما من هي وقت اجازه نمي دم که دستيارم با شکم شنه از اينجا بره
You'll dine with me and then my driver will transport you...
با من شام مي خوري و بعدش هم من مي برمت فروداه
to the airport for the Boston Shuttle departing at 2200 hours.
تا با رواز بوستون برردي و 2200ساعت هم جلو بيافتي
Meanwhile, unpack my bag.
بذريم که مدونم  رو باز نکردي
I'm gonna christen the latrine.
من بايد برم دستشويي
[ Frank ] What's your name, driver ?
راننده اسمت يه؟
- Manny, sir. - Manny.
ماني آقا ماني
The bellhops at the Waldorf, are they any good at getting escorts ?
به نظرت يشخدمتهاي والدرف به خوبي نهبانهاش هستند؟
- I wouldn't know, sir. - What would you know ?
نمي دونم قربان س ي رو مي دوني؟
- About what ? - About you-know-what ?
در مورد ي؟ در مورد يزي که بايد بدوني؟
Maybe I could manage something.
شايد يه روزي بتونم مديرت جايي رو انجام بدم
[ Frank ] I'm talkin' top of the line, now.
مي خوام بدونم که ه کار مي خواي بکني
Let me think about this, sir.
بزاريد يکمي فکر کنم
What's the matter with you ?
تو ته؟
- With me ? - Yeah. Car feels heavy. You know why ?
من؟ آره ،ماشين يکمي سنين حرکت مي کنه، علتش رو مي دوني؟
You got the fuckin' weight of the world on your shoulders.
تو الان تمام سنيني دنيا رو داري با خودت حمل مي کني
I got a little problem at school, that's all.
يزي نيست فقط يه مشکلي توي مدرسه ست
- Spit it out ! - It's not a big deal, all right ?
فکرش رو هم نکن مسئله مهمي نيست
Where we going, the Oak Room or somethin' ?
ما کجا داريم مي ريم،اتاق اوک يا جاي ديه؟
If it's not a big deal, why did you say "real important stuff" ?
اه مسئله مهمي نيست س را مي ي که بايد برم به کارهاي مهمي برسم
What are you doin', banging the dean's daughter ? Hah !
ي کار کردي موهاي دختر مديرتون رو از ته کوتاه کردي؟
- I'm just in a little trouble. - What kind of trouble ?
فقط يه مشکل کويکه ه نوع مشکلي؟
I saw some guys doing something.
ندتا سر رو ديدم که کارهايي مي کنند
To tell or not to tell, or it's your ass.
ه بي ه ني مهم نيست شايد هم از حماقتت باشه
- How'd you know that ? - I'm a wizard.
از کجا خبر داري؟ من ذهن آدمها رو مي خونم
Give me the details, come on.
زودباش جزئيات بيشتري رو بهم بو
There's this guy at school named Harry.
يه سري توي مدرسه ست که اسمش هري ست
He's this real rich kid.
از اونهايي که ولشون از ارو بالا مي ره
He like... runs the show.
اون مي خواست يه نمايش ترتيب بده
Who else ?
ديه کي هست؟
There's another guy, George, but George didn't do anything.
يکي ديه هم اسمش جرج هست اما اون کاري انجام نداد
George and I saw Harry and his buddies doin' somethin'.
من و جرج، هري و دوستاش رو ديديم که ه کار مي کنند
Now, the folks at Baird,
حالا رؤساي بيرد
they know you and George can identify the guilty parties ?
مي دونند که تو و جرج مي دونيد خرابکاري کار کيه؟
Yeah, they think we can.
آره  اونها فکر مي کنند که ما مي تونيم حدس بزنيم کيا بودند
- George is a friend of yours. - He's not a friend, but he's all right.
جرج دوستت هست دوست صميمي که نه اما بهر حال دوستمه
- You trust him ? - Yeah, I guess so.
تو بهش اعتماد داري؟ آره فکر کنم که دارم
- He's on scholarship too ? - No, why ?
اون هم بورسيه ست؟ نه را مي رسيد؟
We got George, we got Harry, we got trouble.
ما جرج رو داريم، هري رو داريم و از همه مهمتر يه مشکل داريم
They're rich, you're poor. You wanna get rich.
اونها ولدارند و تو بي ول و تو هم مي خواي ولدار بشي
You wanna graduate Baird, become a rich big shot like them.
تو هم مي خواي مثل يکي از اون ثروتمندها از بيرد فارغ التحصيل بشي
- Am I right ? - No. It's not that way at all.
درست مي م؟ نه اينطورها هم نيست
Okay, Charlie !
بسيار خب ارلي
Here we are, gentlemen: the Oak Room.
بفرماييد آقايون اين هم سالن اوک
The Oak Room !
سالن بلوط
Bring us a menu and double Jack Daniels on the rocks.
برامون منو غذا رو بياريد روي ميز هم مشروب جک دانيلز رو دو برابر کنيد
Charlie, sit down here.
ارلي اينجا بشين
Uh, perhaps you'll feel more comfortable in this, sir.
قربان حتما شما با اين لباس راحتر خواهيد بود
[ Wolf Whistle ] You look great !
خوش تي شدي
Thank you.
ممنونم
Here we are, Charlie: the Oak Room.
خب ارلي حالا ما در سالن بلوط هستيم
Now, read me the bill of fare.
برام قيمت غذاها رو بخون
Uh, let's see.
بزاريد ببينم
You got the Oak Room Burger and fries for $24.
اه وشت سرخ کرده و برر اينجا رو بخواييد ميشه 24دلار
Where's the booze ? Flowin' like mud around here.
مشروب هاش طور؟ بدون اون اصلا غذا مزه اي نداره
A $24 hamburger ?
24دلار براي  همبرر؟
W-What's the story ?
باورم نمي شه؟
What story ?
را باورت نمي شه؟
- Are you a rich miser or something ? - Hah !
خلاصه من نفهميدم شما خسيس هستيد يا نه؟
No, I'm just your average blind man.
من فقط يه آدم نسبتا کورم
Your average blind man.
درسته که شما نمي بينيد
How do you plan on paying for all this stuff ?
اما شما طوري براي خرج کردم اين ول برنامه ريزي مي کنيد؟
Crisp, clean dollars... American.
بيخيال ما فقط بايد دلارهاي آمريکايي رو سربه نيست کنيم
I saved up my disability checks.
من ولها و ک هاي دوران ناتواني ام رو س انداز کردم
How much did you save ? I mean, we flew first class,
طوري؟ منظورم اينه که ما با بليط درجه يک همه اش رو داريم خرج مي کنيم
we're at the Waldorf-Astoria, a $24 hamburger restaurant.
بع هتل والدورف استريا مي يام و 24دلار مي ديم براي يه همبرر
- All part of a plan, Charlie. - You want to let me in on it ?
اين يه بخشي از برنامه ست مي خواييد که اينجا بمونم؟
Why should I ? You're not interested. You don't give a shit !
را بايد اين کار رو بکنم؟ تو که دوست نداري
You're leavin' on that last shuttle out of La Guardia.
تو با آخرين قطار لاارديا از اينجا ميري
You got 15 minutes, son. I don't think you're gonna make it,
هي سر تو دقيقا 15 دقيقه وقت منو رفتي درست مي م يا نه
unless the Oak Room keeps some complimentary helicopter on the roof.
نکنه مي خواي مدير اينجا يه بليط افتخاري هليکوتر روي شت بوم رو مهمونت کنه
No, sir. No !
نه نه
You're here till tomorrow.
تو تا فردا اينجا مي موني
You said the last shuttle leaves at 2200 hours.
شما که فتي آخريت قطار 2200ساعت ديه مي ره
That's 10:00, right ?
درست راس ساعت 10؟
Last I heard, yeah.
بله درسته من همينطور شنيدم که بهت فتم
It's only 8:30.
الان8:15 دقيقه ست
I lied. Leaves at 9:00.
دروغ بهت فتم، ساعت 9حرکت مي کنه
- It leaves at 9:00 ? - Calm down. Calm down.
ساعت 9حرکت مي کنه؟ آروم باش آروم
Ahh ! The truth is, Charlie,
راستش ارلي
- I need a guide dog to help me execute my plan. - What plan ?
من يه س راهنما نياز دارم تا منو در انجام برنامه ريزي ام کمک کنه ه برنامه اي؟ه نقشه اي؟
You have a right to know.
تو حق داري که بدوني
It's not really a plan, Charlie. It's sort of a --
در حقيقت من اصلا برنامه اي ندارم اين بيشتر شبيه يه
more like a tour,
ردشريه
a little tour of pleasures:
ند روزي رو خوش بذرونيم
stay in a first-class hotel, eat an agreeable meal,
توي هتل درجه يک بخوابيم غذاهاي لذيذ و خوشمزه بخوريم
drink a nice glass of wine,
مشروبهاي خنک و مطبوعي بنوشيم
see my big brother.
و برادر بزرم رو ببينم
Nothing like family, you know.
البته بايد بدوني که اون جزو فاميلم نيست
And then, make love to a terrific woman.
و بالاخره زن مورد علاقه خودم رو ملاقات کنم
After that...
بعد از اون هم
Yeah ?
ي؟
I'm gonna lie down on my big, beautiful bed at the Waldorf...
ميرم و روي تخت خوشخواب هتل مي خوابم
and blow my brains out.
و مغرم با لوله مي ترکونم
- May I tell you our specials ? - You may, sir.
مي تونم غذاي مخصوص امشبمون رو بهتون معرفي کنم؟ البته آقا
Tonight we have charred venison with buckwheat spaetzle and green peppercorn.
امشب اينجا يه نوع کباب مخصوص ذغالي وشت آهو به همراه فلفل سبز سرو مي شه
Grilled veal, tomato tapenade, and roasted eggplants.
وشت وساله سرخ شده با سيب زميني و بادنجان کبابي
Get me a napkin. My mouth's watering.
دستمالم رو بده دهنم خيسه
If you like our souffle for dessert, it would be good to order it now.
ار هم دوست داريد دسر امشب رو که يه نوع خوراک با زرده تخم مرغ و وشت و نير و شکلاته رو هم مي تونيد سفارش بديد خوشحال ميشيم سفارش شما رو انجام بديم
Yes, on the souffle. Give us a half a minute on the rest.
بله حتما اين کار و بکنيد تا يک دقيقه ديه اين دسر رو مي خوام
Very good, sir.
بسيار خب قربان
- I'm leaning towards the spaetzle. - Colonel Slade --
من عاشق غذاي امشبم کلنل اسليد
Charlie, rolls on the table ? Give 'em to me.
ارلي سبد نون روي ميزه؟ بدش به من
You should try these rolls.
اين کار رو که مي توني انجام بدي
I used to dream about them when I was at Fort Huachuca.
وقتيکه در فورت هااکا بودم همش خوابش رو مي ديدم
- Colonel Slade -- - Bread's no good west of the Colorado.
کلنل اسليد نونهاي غرب کلرادو اصلا خوب نيستند
- Water's too alkaline. - Colonel Slade, did you say --
آبش هم خيلي قلياييه کلنل اسليد شما فتيد
Did I hear you right ?
من درست شنيدم؟
Y-You said you're gonna kill yourself ?
فتيد که مي خواييد خودتون رو بکشيد؟
No, I said I was gonna blow my brains out.
نه من فتم که مي خوام مغزم رو بترکونم
Try one of these rolls, Charlie. I buttered it for ya.
ارلي يکي از اينها رو امتحان کن الان برات روش کره مي مالم
I don't want a roll, all right ?
نه نمي خوام
Okay. Have a radish !
باشه حداقل يکم تربه بخور
Hello ! Bring me a double Jack Daniels on the rocks.
سلام دو تا ليوانهاي منو از جک دانيلز ر کن
Yes, sir. Right away.
شم قربان
Please, don't do that.
خواهش مي کنم اينکار رو نکن
Don't do that.
اينکار رو نکن
What a marvelous place !
جاي خارق العاده ايه
Okay.
بسيار خب
Yeah.
آره درسته
Your billet is here.
جاي خوابت اينجاست
You'll find bedding in the closet on the shelf.
اينجا شبها تبديل به اتاق خواب مي شه مي توني اينجا بخوابي
In the morning, the area will be returned to sitting-room mode...
صبح ها هم دوباره به وضعيت اولش برمي رده و ميشه اتاق نشيمن
no later than 0700 hours.
قبل از ساعت 7 صبح اينجا بايد جمع و جور باشه
What was that ?
اون ي بود؟
Nothing.
هيي
Next time... snap it out !
دفعه ديه خواستي اينکار رو بکني بايد سفت و محکم بياريش ايين
Thumb to palm, index finger through little digit, smartly aligned,
شصتت رو به کف دست، انشت اشاره ات هم نزديک به بقيه انشتها دقيقا کنار هم
sharp to the hairline, down !
مستقيم و راست بيارشون ايين
Too many men, far better than you,
خيلي ها رو ديدم که بهتر از تو اينکار رو انجام مي دند
have executed that courtesy.
در واقع اونها ادب و احترام رو به جا مي يارند
And if you're smart, you won't try it again.
اه بلد نيستي بهتر اصلا انجامش ندي
This bat has got sharper radar than the Nautilus.
من رادارهاي خوبي براي دريافت وقايع دارم
Don't fuck with me, Charlie.
س بهتره که با من شوخي نکني، ارلي
See you get a good night's sleep, son.
اميدوارم خواب خوبي داشته باشي سر
[ Frank ] § It's a lovely day today §
امروز روز قشنيه
§ So, whatever you gotta do §
س تو مي توني هر کاري که
§ You got a lovely day to do it in that's true §
مي خواي توي اين روز زيبا انجام بدي، بده ون کار درستيه
Good morning, Charlie.
صبح بخير ارلي
- [ Sigh ] Good morning. - This is Sofia, Charlie.
صبح بخير اين سوفيا ست ارلي
She's a magician with a needle.
اون با نخ و سوزنش واقعا جادو مي کنه
Sofia's workin' me up a little "Glen Plaid" number,
سوفيا لباسهاي منو مي دوزه
and I've asked her if she'd put something together for you.
اه بخواي براي تو هم مي تونه يه دست بدوزه
- Uh, I don't need any clothes, Colonel. - Standard issue...
نه کلنل من لباس احتياج ندارم يه لباس رسمي و موقر
for an upscale urban assignment.
براي يه دانش آموز بد هيکل
You don't like the clothes, Charlie, on completion of duty,
تو براي اينکه از سر خودت وا کني
you can give 'em away.
مي ي لباس نمي خواي ، مي خواي فرار کني
Juice, coffee, and other assorted goodies on the trolley over there.
آبميوه ،قهوه و بقيه خوراکي هاي صبحونه ، همشون اونجاست
Get yourself up, get yourself together !
اشو يالا بلند شو از رت در بيا يالا
§ It's a great day for singin' a song §
امروز روز خوبي براي خوندن يه آواز دل انيزه
§ And it's a great day for movin' along §
يه روز خوب براي يه ياده روي طولاني
from morning to night §
يه روز دلنشين براي به ايان رسوندن صبح تا شب
§ And it's a great day §
و يه روز خوب
for everybody's plight.
براي عمل کردن به قول و قرارها
How are you feeling today, Colonel ?
امروز حالتون ه طور کلنل؟ خوبيد؟
Super ! Superior !
البته عاليه بهتر از اين نمي شه
Superfluous !
خارق العاده ست
Young Sofie here is working Thanksgiving...
سوفي جوان در اينجا داري مراسم شکرزاري رو انجام مي ده
because she's trying to put herself through college.
براي اينکه قصد داره وقت خودش رو در اختيار کالج بزاره
I told her, "My young friend Charlie's headed for college."
بهش فتم که" دوست جوون من نماينده دانش آموزهاي کالجه
- Uh, excuse me. - Where you goin' ?
ببخشيد کجا ميري؟
- I-l need to use the phone. - What's wrong with the phones in here ?
بايد يه تلفن بزنم مه زن زدن از اينجا ه اشکالي داره؟
I don't want to disturb you.
نمي خوام ناراحتتون کنم
You're not disturbing me. Make your call.
درسته نمي خواي اذيتم کني برو زنت رو بزن
I'd kinda like to be private.
بايد خصوصي صحبت کنم
Stay outta my room !
توي اتاق من بمون
This is as private as you're gonna get.
اينجا هم مي توني خصوصي صحبت کني
§ But if you've got somethin' that must be done §
اما اه مي خواي بري کار ديه اي انجام بدي
§ And it can only be done by one §
مي توني تنهايي بري بيرون
Sofia...
سوفيا
what are the chances of suitin' you up sometime ?
واقعا شانس آوردم که تو لباس برام مي دوزي؟
- [ Operator ] Sugarbush Lodge. - George Willis, please.
شوربراش لوج لطفا جرج ويليس
- [ George ] Hello ! - George ! Hey, it's Charlie.
سلام جرج منم ارلي
Hey, Chas. Next year you gotta come up with us.
هي اس سال ديه بايد حتما با ما بيايي
White powder on a base of snow bunnies.
بيايي و اينجا اسکي کني
Chas, are you there ?
اس وشي دستته؟
Yeah, I'm here. Um --
آره آره
- you told me to call you for the moves. - All right.
بهم فته بودي که هرکاري داشتم باهات تماس بيرم درسته
For now, the move's no move: status quo.
اما از الان به بعد کار بي کار
Everything's the way we left it.
بزار همه يز روال عادي خودش رو طي کنه
How did we leave it ?
طوري مي تونيم همين طور دست رو دست بزاريم؟
See no evil, hear no evil.
شتر ديدي ،نديدي نه يزي شنيدي،نه يزي ديدي
You know what I mean, Chas ?
مي دوني منظورم يه،اس؟
Yeah. See no evil, hear no evil.
آره، شتر ديدي نديدي
- Okay, then, walk like you talk ! - All right, good-bye.
حالا شد، برو برس به زنديت باشه خداحافظ
- George Willis, huh ? - Yeah.
جرج ويليس آره؟ بله
George Willis.
جرج ويليس
That makes his father probably George Willis, Senior.
حتما هم درش يه آدم سرشناس و مهميه
Charlie, I ask ya,
ارلي مي خوام بدونم
what do you think Big George is gonna feel about Little George...
فکر مي کني جرج بزر در مورد اونکه جرج کويک فت
seeing no evil, hearing no evil ?
شتر ديدي نديدي، ه فکري مي کنه؟
Well, we're not gonna tell our parents.
خب ما نمي خواييم به درها و مادرامون يزي بيم
We're just gonna keep it between ourselves.
اين فقط بين خودمون مي مونه
Oh, George isn't gonna tell his father about this thing !
آهان جرج نمي خواد يزي در مورد اين جريان به درش به
Damn decent of him. Ooh ! Aw ! Hah !
لعنت بهش
- Scusi. - Prego.
ببخشيد مهم نيست
I love it when you hurt me.
اه منو اذيت هم بکني بازم خوشم مي ياد
Uh, tell me now, Charlie.
خب حالا بهم بو ببينم ارلي
This, uh, George Willis, Junior, what's his father do ?
اين در جرج ويليس کويک ه کاره ست؟
I don't really know.
اصلا نمي دونم
Well, I'm gonna tell ya.
خب من بهت مي م
When George Willis, Sr., isn't busy as a million-dollar man for Aetna Casualty --
تصادفا اين سر جرج ويليس يه ميليونره که سرش هم اصلا شلوغ نيست
or is it New England Distributor for the Chrysler Corporation ?
شايد هم يکي از مهمره هاي انليسي باشه که توي شرکت کريسلر دستي داره؟
He concerns himself with his young son, George Willis, Junior.
اون براي جرج ويليس کوک ، سرش ،اهميت قائله
George isn't going to say anything to his father.
جرج يزي در اين باره به درش نمي ه
Oh, Charlie.
ارلي
Big George is gonna wind up Little George,
جرج بزر با جرج کوک اتمام حجت مي کنه
and Little George is gonna sing like a canary.
و جرج کويک هم مثل يه قناري براي درش آواز مي خونه
And if you're hip, kid, you're gonna hop to, too.
و اه تو بخواي اين وسط دست دست کني رت مي دند و فرار مي کني
You've got this all figured out, don't you ?
و شما از يه تلفن اين همه مطلب متوجه شديد؟
It don't take no Young America merit scholarship to figure this one out.
من نمي خوام يه دانش آموزي از بورسيه تحصيلي محروم بمونه
Charlie, you had a little life, so you decided to go to Baird...
ارلي تو زندي محدودي داري س راهي جز رفتن به بيرد نداري
to put yourself in the market for a big one.
و بايد خودت رو در اختيار قويترها قرار بدي
Now, in order to stay in the running,
حالا اه مي خواي به اين راه ادامه بدي
you're gonna have to tell these people what they want to know.
س بهتره بدوني که مجبوري اونکه اين مردم مي خواند بدونند رو بهشون بي
You think so ?
شما اينطور فکر مي کنيد؟
- Are we finished, Sofia ? - Yes.
کارمون تموم شد سوفيا؟ بله
Grazie. Grazie.
ممنونم
Charlie,
ارلي
if you don't sing now,
اه الان نخواي مثل يه قناري بخوني
you're gonna end up, not only shelving biscuits...
مجبوي همه يز رو بزراي کنار تنها طبقه بندي بيسکوييت
in some convenience store in the Oregon burbs,
در مجتمع رفاهي ايالت ارون نسيبت مي شه
probably the last word you'll ever hear yourself say just before you croak...
حتي شايد آخرين کلمه اي که بشنوي صداي قورباغه اي خودته که به مشتري ها مي ي
gonna be, "Have a nice day and come back soon."
روز خوبي داشته باشيد و اميدوارم دوباره به اين فروشاه بررديد
Sofia !
سوفيا
Measure up Charlie, pronto. We got a date for Thanksgiving.
سريع ارلي رو آماده کن مي خواييم امروز روز شکر زاري ما باشه
We got a date ?
ه روزي؟
My brother's place.
مي ريم منزل برادرم
W.R. Slade, White Plains, New York.
وي.آر. اسليد ساکن خيابون وايت لينز  نيويورک
Colonel, I can't go with you to your brother's place.
کلنل من نمي تونم با شما بيام منزل برادرتون
I mean, I should be getting back to school.
من بايد برردم مدرسه
Uh, well you gotta have Thanksgiving somewhere.
آهان بو مي خواي مراسم شکرزاري رو جاي ديه انجام بدي
I mean, eats and treats. I could use the company.
مي خواستم دور هم باشيم و غذايي بخوريم
All right. D-Does he know I'm comin' ?
باشه حالا اون مي دونه که من هم اومدم؟
He doesn't know I'm comin'. But wait till you see the look on his face...
اون حتي نمي دونه که من اومدم يکم ديه صبر کن بايد وقتيکه
when I walk through the door.
ما رو جلوي در مي بينه، تماشاش کني
Oh, he loves me !
اما دوستم داره
Oh, uh, Charlie, about your little problem,
ارلي ، در مورد اون مسئله کويکت
there are two kinds of people in this world:
دو روه آدم توي دنيا وجود دارند
those who stand up and face the music,
يه روه که علنأ جلوي موسيقي مي ايستند
and those who run for cover.
و روه دوم مخفيانه با موسيقي مخالفت مي کنند
Cover's better. Okay, Sofia, suit 'im up !
روش مخفيانه بهتره بسيار خب سوفيا زود حاضرش کن
Make him pretty !
خوش تيش کن
Careful.
مواظب باش
- Should I ring it ? - Yeah.
من بايد زن بزنم؟ آره
Yes ?
بفرماييد؟
Yes ! Who is this ?
شما؟
- It's Randy. - Randy ? You new ?
من رندي ام رندي؟ تازه واردي؟
I'm your nephew.
برادر زادتون هستم
Hah ! Here I am !
خب من هم اينجام
Your sister's been hoarding me long enough.
خواهرت به اندازه کافي مراقب من بوده
- Thought it's time to spread the riches around. - Uncle Frank !
ديه وقتشه که يکم ولها رو خرج کنم عمو فرانک
- Gloria ! - Gail.
لوريا يل
Of course.
درسته يل
Say hello to the potluck party from New York City.
به ميزبانهاي نيويورکي سلام کن
Good old Uncle Frank and this here with him is Charlie Simms,
عمو فرانک ير و دوست داشتني و ارلي سيمسز
star halfback of the Baird football team.
اون ستاره تيم فوتبال مدرسه بيرد هست
They not only beat Exeter and Groton, but Aquinas High School too.
اونها نه تنها به تيم اکستر و روتون ل زدند حتي تونستند از تيم آکوانس هم ببرند
Where's your miserable father ?
در بدبخت و بياره ات کجاست؟
Wait ! No, no. Let's surprise him.
صبر کن نه نه وايستا مي خوام غافليرش کنم
Give that fat heart of his an attack. Willie !
بزار اون قلب ر از ربي اش از ترس وايسته و سکته کنه ويلي
Hello, Frank.
سلام فرانک
- How you doin' ? - Okay.
طوري؟ خوبم
Here's my hand. Charlie, meet W.R. Slade.
دستم اينجاست ارلي با وي.آر. اسليد آشنا شو
Nice to meet you, sir.
از ديدنتون خوشبختم آقا
The original bulging briefcase man.
مردي که در شکم ندي لنه نداره
Gretchen, I smell those prunes ! We talkin' Turkey Marbella ?
رن، بوي اون آلوها به مشام رسيده مه ما ازت بوقلمون خواسته بوديم
- Yes, we are. - Whoo !
آره درست مي ي
Let's have a whiff. Come on.
بيا با هم يه خوش آمدويي بکنيم
You know, I always had a sneaker for you. Come here.
مي دوني که هميشه عادت داشتم يواشکي اينکار بکنم بيا يالا
- Where are you, Garry ? I heard you cough. - Who are you again ?
ري تو کجايي؟ صداي سرفه ات رو شنيدم تو کي هستي ديه؟
I'm just here at the Waldorf-Astoria with -- Is it your brother ?
من فقط  توي هتل والدورف استريا باهاش هستم مه اين برادرتون نيست؟
W.R.'s final issue. How ya doin' ?
آخرين فرزند وي.آر طوري؟
- Yes. Who the hell are you ? - I'm kinda takin' care of him for the weekend.
آره خودشه اما تو ه غلطي مي کني؟ قراره که آخر هفته از ايشون مراقبت کنم
Charlie !
ارلي
Jesus !
خداي من
Sorry. Where's the booze ? Flowin' like mud here.
متاسفم. مشروب کجاست؟ لوم خشک شده
To tell the truth, the colonel's not well, I don't think.
يه حقيقتي رو مي خواستم بهتون بم فکر کنم حال ايشون اصلا خوب نباشه
- Not well ? - I think he's a little lonely.
خوب نيست؟ فکر کنم اون خيلي تنهاست
Why didn't you take him to your family's for dinner ?
را نبرديش به خونه اقوام خودت براي مهموني و شام؟
I heard that !
شنيدم ي فتي
I heard that.
شنيدم
Pay no attention to him. That's his big-brother talk.
خيلي بهش توجه نکن اين برادر بزر زياد حرف مي زنه
He's been watching out for me since day one.
اون از ديروز انتظار منو مي کشيده
Bailed me out of more trouble... than he'd like to remember.
منو با مشکلاتم تنها بزاريد ره اون دوست داره يادآوري کنه
- Hmm ? - [ Gretchen ] Let me take your coat.
کتتون رو بديد به من
I meant to pick up some vino on my way, but I blew it.
نمي خواستم بيام اينجا ولي نشد
I'll send you the Rothschild again for Christmas,
بهر حال دوباره براي کريسمس برات کارت ستال مي فرستم
- only let's see how Thanksgiving goes. - I'll set two more places.
دليلش هم فقط اينه که بدوني مراسم شکرزاري در يشه دو تا جا مي رم و براتون درست مي کنم
- Here's your drink, Frank. - Thank you, Randy.
اين هم نوشيدني ممنونم رندي
Still with Snow Queen sugar ?
هنوز توي اين اون شرکت هستي؟
Snow Flake. Why do you always get that wrong ?
اسمش اسنو فليکه طور شما هنوز نمي دونيد؟
Because it's not important for me to get it right. What are you doing there ?
براي اينکه اصلا برام مهم نيست اونجا ه کار مي کني؟
I'm Vice President for Marketing.
معاون مدير فروش شکر هستم
Whoo-ah ! Congratulations ! Sugar is shit, though.
بهت تبريک مي م بهر حال شکر هم يز بدي نيست
I told General Abrams to install honey in the commissaries.
به آبراهام اصلي فتم که يه فروشاه تعاوني مصرف کارکنان داير کنه
If the K-50s didn't blow your brains out, sugar, sure as shit, was gonna.
اه توي کله ات مغزي وجود نداشته باشه جاش مي توني ازشکر توش ر کني
- Why don't we all sit down ? - Ooh !
را نمي ريم نمي شينيم؟
Mitsouki. Rhymes with nookie. Be careful.
مراقب عطرهايي که زدي باش
- When the wife gets restless, the wife gets racy. - Let's go and eat.
وقتي همسر يکي بخواد يه جا استراحت کنه و بشينه جز جلف بازي کار ديه اي نمي کنه بياييد بريم و غذا بخوريم
By all means. Thank you, Charlie.
بذريم ممنونم ارلي
Where you wanna sit, Frank, or you gonna arrange yourself at the head again ?
مي خواي کجا بشيني فرانک ، هر جا رو دوست داري انتخاب کن و برو
Any old card table will do. This is fine.
هي کدوم از کارتهاي قديمي روي ميز نيست همين جا خوبه
[ Frank ] Where was I ? Oh !
کجا بودم؟ آهان
I wake up. It's four in the morning. I don't know who I'm with,
از خواب بيدار شدم.ساعت 4صبح بود نمي دونستم يش کي ام
why I'm there and where I am.
را اونجام و اصلا کجام
What am I gonna do ? I got this Asian flower,
نمي دونستم ه کاري بايد بکنم يه دسته از اون لهاي آسيايي رو رفتم
all giggly and dewy-like;
همشون تر و تازه بودند شبنم روشون هنوز از بين نرفته بود
and this hard-boiled navy nurse outta Omaha, on the other.
و اون رستار ديرجوش نيروي دريايي ارتش اوماهايي هم اون طرف ايستاده بود
We're three across the bed, not a stitch of clothes on.
سه بار اينطرف و اونطرف تخت خواب رفتيم لباسها هم هي کدومشون دوختي نداشتند
It comes to me.
به طرف من اومد
Let east meet west. We'll build a golden bridge.
از سمت شرق به سمت غرب و ما تونستيم ل طلايي رو با هم بسازيم
I felt like I'd just joined the corps of engineers !
احساس کردم با اين کار مي تونم يه همکاري رو در مهندسها ايجاد کنم
We all still here ?
حواسها هست؟
It's a beautiful story. [ Cough ]
داستان قشني بود
- Do you always enjoy shocking people, Uncle Frank ? - Honey.
عمو فرانک از اينکه اطرافيانتون رو شوکه و هيجانزده کنيد لذت مي بريد؟ عزيزم
I didn't know you were so easily shocked.
فکر نکنم تو حتي ذره اي شوکه شده باشي
I admire your sensibilities. I'm touched.
حساسيت تو رو تحسين مي کنم مي تونم حسش کنم
Dad, remember the time you persuaded Frank...
در يادت مي ياد موقعيکه فرانک رو ترغيب کرديد
- to go to the kennel ? - What about it ?
بره توي لونه سها زندي کنه؟ خب که ي؟
- He almost put the seeing eye dog business outta business. - Cool it, Randy.
ون فقط عادت داشتي که شم توي شم سها بندازي بس کن رندي
- It's over and done with. - Indeed it is, Garry.
خودش مي خواست درسته ري
Indeed it is. So is dinner.
حق با توست خب بريم سر غذا
Charlie, what time do you have ? I think we better be gettin' back.
ارلي ساعتت نده؟ فکر کنم بهتر باشه بررديم
- You ever given any thought to a braille watch, Frank ? - Randy.
را يه ساعت نوشته شده با خط بريل به دست نمي کنيد؟ رندي
- Stevie Wonder wears one, or do you rank on him too ? - Honey, please.
استيو واندر هم از اونا داره، نکنه فکر مي کنيد شما بالاتر از اون هستيد؟ عزيزم خواهش مي کنم
It's all right, Gloria. I enjoy Randy's observations.
کاملا درسته لوريا من از نظرات رندي لذت مي برم
My wife's name is Gail, Frank. Can you hear that ? Gail.
فرانک اسم همسر من يل هست مي توني که بشنوي؟ يل
Excuse me. Gail.
ببخشيد يل
Gail strikes me as a very beautiful woman,
به نظرم يل زن زيباييه
but there's a little tension in her voice.
اما صداش يکمي زن داره
It could be one of two things:
علتش هم مي تونه به دو دليل باشه
either Gail is nervous or unsatisfied.
يا يل عصبيه و يا ناراضي
What's your point, Uncle Frank ?
مشکلي داري عمو فرانک؟
You oughta go down on her.
جفتتون بريد به جهنم
Cut it out, Frank, will ya ?
بس کن فرانک ميشه؟
You're so wrapped up in sugar, you've forgotten the taste of real honey !
وقتيکه مي خواي اونو توي يه ظرف عسل نه داري و حلوا حلواش کني اصلا يادت ميره طعم و مزه واقعي عسل يه
Frank, for God's sake !
فرانک به خاطر خدا
Hear that voice ? There's fire under that dress.
صداش رو شنيديد؟ ايناري که آتيش زير لباسش مي سوزونند
- Will you cut it out ? - Just get the fuck outta here.
ميشه تمومش کني؟ فقط از اينجا ورت رو م کن
- Whoo-ah ! - Get in your limousine.
برو و سوار اون ليموزينت بشو و م شو
Go down to the bowery, get with the other fucking drunks where you belong !
برو به هر جهنمي که مي خواي و تا حد مر هم مشروب بخور
- Wait a minute. - What ?
يه لحظه صبر کنيد تو ديه ي مي ي؟
- Could you take it easy ? - What for ?
را اينقدر سخت مي يريد؟ ي رو؟
You want me to lay off him, Chuckie, 'cause he's blind ?
اک مي خواي ون اين کوره همين طور وايستم تا هر ي که مي خواد به؟
- No, but I mean -- - My friend's name is Charles.
نه من منظورم اينه که اسم دوست من ارلز
He doesn't like to be called Chuckie.
دوست نداره به اين اسم صداش کني
- This is supposed to be a family get-together. This is -- - A warning.
همه اعضاء خانواده اينجاست، ميشه تمومش کنيد اين يه هشداره
Jesus Christ. Another sucker who thinks this shitheel's a war hero.
خداي من ببينيد اين ي مي ه هنوز دهنش بوي شير مي ده مي خواد براي من وساطت کنه
Well, once... maybe.
خب يه بار ديه تکرار شد
I suppose he told you about his days on Lyndon Johnson's staff ?
فکر کنم درباره اون روزي که توي ستاد ارتش ليندون جانسون بوده براتون يه يزهايي تعريف کرده باشه؟
I was gonna go. Now I'm not leaving.
اون روز رفته بودم بيرون اما الان اينجا رو ترک نمي کنم
- Frank was earmarked for general. - Earmarked, good word.
به فرانک يه نشون افتخار داده شد نشان افتخار، واژه خوبي به کار بردي
- But Frank likes to spit in everybody's eye ! - Randy, that's enough.
اما فرانک دوست داره شم همه رو از کاسه در بياره رندي کافيه
So -- What do they call it when they give you the shaft in the military ?
خب ي مي ي وقتيکه اونها در ارتش ازت خواستند تيراندازي کني؟
- Passed over ! - Frank was passed over for promotion...
تخته هدف افتاد خوبه به خاطر ترفيع و تشويق تخته هدف خودش مي افته
Couple times.
اون هم دو بار
- You want to know what happened then ? - Will you shut your mouth ?
مي خواي بدوني بعدش ي شد؟ مي توني دهنت رو ببندي؟
- He blew himself up. - Stop it, Randy.
به خودش تيراندازي کرد بس کن رندي
Our colonel, here, had a grenade juggling act at Fort Bragg or wherever.
کلنل ما، در اينجا درست مثل فورت بر با نارنجک تردستي مي کنه
- Fort Benning. - He was teaching hand-to-hand combat --
فورت بنين اون جن تن به تن آموزش مي داد
Randy, look at me when you're talking to me, son.
رندي،سر، وقتيکه با من صحبت مي کني به من ناه کن
I'm lookin', Frank. His partner in the act was some captain.
نات مي کنم فرانک همرزمش هم توي اون عمليات يه کايتان بود
- Major Vincent Squires. - Yeah, whoever he was.
سررد وينسون واقعا يه سلحشور بود آره هموني که خودت مي ي
Before going on, they'd have themselves a lo-cal breakfast:
قبل از اينکه برند با هم يه صبحانه مي خورند
a Screwdriver for Frank, Bloody Mary for his partner.
اون آارفرانسه فرانک بود بساط مشروبشون هم هميشه جور بود
No, Vincent drank Sea Breezes.
نه وينسون هميشه عادت داشت مارک بريز بخوره
Judge Advocate at Benning said Col. Slade had four to his partner's one.
قاضي از اين کلنل دفاع کرد امتياز اسليد هار و همکارش يک شد
He's flying in class. He gets all excited.
اين قدر هيجانزده بود که توي کلاس مي خواس رواز مي کرد
He starts pulling the pins out.
از اونجا ديه رفاقتش رو بهم زد
[ Randy ] One grenade got away from him.
يه نارنجک هم بست بهش و
Boom.
ترکيد
The one that got away.
اون خودش فرار کرد
Oh, the pin was in... Frank claims.
ادعاش هم فقط اون سنجاقهاست
In or out, what difference does it make ?
باشه يا نباشه ه فرقي مي کنه؟
What kind of fucking lunatic juggles grenades ?
اين کار فقط از يه آدم ديوونه و مجنون بر مي ياد تا با نارنجک تردستي کنه
Vinnie came out okay.
ويني جون سالم بدر برد
And all Frank lost was his eyesight.
و فرانک هم ديد شمهاش رو از دست داد
- Wanna know the truth ? - You got a handle on that, do you, Randy ?
مي خواي حقيقت رو بدوني؟ رندي داري يه دستمايه درست مي کني؟
- He was an asshole before. - Whoo-ah !
اون قبلا هم ديوونه و احمق بود
Now all he is is a blind asshole.
حالا هم يه ديوونه کوره
Hey, God's a funny guy.
بهرحال خدا هم موجود شوخيه
God doth have a sense of humor.
خداوند براي بشر حس رو خلق کرده
Maybe God thinks some people don't deserve to see.
شايد هم خدا فکر مي کنه بعضي از مردم شايستي ديدن رو ندارند
You get the point... Chuckie ?
اک جريان رو فهميدي؟
- Aah ! - His name is Charles.
اسمش ارلز هست
You can say that, can't you ? Charles.
مي توني بي ارلز درسته؟ مي توني
Know what this is, Randy ? It's a choke hold I'm teaching those lieutenants.
مي دوني يه رندي؟ من اين تخصص خفه کردن رو به خيلي از افسرها ياد دادم س تو رو هم خيلي راحت مي تونم خفه کنم
- Little pressure, I bust your windpipe. - I don't care what he said.
با يکم فشار مي تونم ناي تو رو ببدم و بشکنمش من به اون ه که فت توجهي نکردم
- Charles. - Just let go, please !
ارلز خواهش مي کنم بيا بريم
Gretchen ?
رن؟
You outdid yourself.
کار تو عالي بود
If you twist my arm hard enough,
اه بتوني همين طور مقاومت کني
we're talking Turkey Marbella next year.
سال ديه مي يام و بوقلمون شب عيدت رو مي خوريم
Who knows ?
کي ه مي دونه؟
Frank ?
فرانک؟
Good-bye, Willie.
خداحافظ  ويلي
I'm no fucking good...
من بازيه نيستم
and I never have been.
و هرز هم نبودم
Come on, Charlie, get the coats.
بيا ارلي، کتم رو بيار
Come on. Watch your step.
بيا جلوي اتون رو ناه کنيد
Hold it.
نهش دار
Nueva York, compadre. Vamos !
نيويورک
You got a watch ?
ساعت دستته؟
Ah, it's 7:20.
7:20
I didn't ask you the time. I asked if you had a watch.
ازت نخواستم که بي ساعت نده ازت رسيدم ساعت داري يا نه
Yeah, in the other room.
بله توي اون يکي اتاق هست
Get it.
بيارش
Colonel, there's a clock right next to your bed.
کلنل دقيقأ يه ساعت کنار تختتون هست
Does it have a second hand ?
دست دومه؟
Yeah.
بله
Time me !
زمان رو برام ثبت کن
How long ?
قدر طول مي کشه؟
Um... about 30 seconds.
حدود 30ثانيه
- I'm rusty. - Where did you get a gun, Colonel ?
حالم اصلا خوش نيست کلنل اين تفن رو از کجا آورديد؟
Piece or weapon, Charlie, never a gun.
اسلحه ارلي نه تفن
Where did you get the piece ?
اسلحه رو از کجا آورديد؟
I'm an officer in the United States Army. This is my sidearm.
من افسر ارتش امريکا هستم. اين اسلحه هم دوست منه
- But you're not an officer anymore. - So I'm retired, so what ?
اما شما که الان نظامي نيستيد آره بازنشست شدم که ي؟
An officer never relinquishes his 45.
يک نظامي هي وقت دوست خودش رو ترک نمي کنه
Yeah, but you better relinquish it to me or I'm gonna call Mrs. Rossi.
بله اما بهتره که بديش به من و الا بايد به خانم روسي بم
Good idea.
ايده خوبيه
Then I'm going back to school.
برمي ردم ميرم مدرسه
Even better. Blue skies, green lights.
بهتر از اين نمي شه آسمون آبس، نورهاي سبز
I hope you have a wonderful trip. That felt like 25.
اميدوارم سفر خوبي داشته باشي
You oughta be able to do a 45 in 25. Did you time me ?
بايد بتوني توي45تا25دقيقه انجام بدي زمان رو برام نه داشتي يا نه؟
No, I did not and I'm calling Albany.
نه اين کار رو نمي کنم بايد با آلباني تماس بيرم
That was stupid.
کارتون خيلي احمقانه بود
Was it ?
احمقانه بود؟
You're stuck with me, Charlie.
بيا نزديکم ارلي
No, I'm not.
نه نمي يام
- I'm outta here ! - Where you goin' ? New Hampshire ?
من اينجام کجا داري ميري؟ نيوهمشاير
You got no money. How you gonna do that ?
ولي نداري ه طوري مي خواي بري؟
Karen's number tastes like Albany. Hah !
شماره تلفن کارن طعم آلباني رو مي داد
Fine.
خوبه
- I'm leaving. - Charlie ? Charlie !
من دارم مي رم ارلي؟ ارلز
All I want from you... is another day.
فقط ازت مي خوام يه روز ديه بموني
For what ?
براي ي؟
One last tour of the battlefield.
براي اخرين سفرم در ميدون جن
I can get around a city like New York,
مي تونم در شهري مثل نيويورک شتي بزنم
but l...
اما من
sometimes need a point in the right direction.
بهضي وقتها نياز يدا مي کنم که راهنمايي بشم
What do you say, Charlie ?
نظرت يه ارلي؟
What's one day... between friends ?
ه نوع ارتباطي مي تونه بين دو دوست وجود داشته باشه؟
All right. Well, say I stay for another day.
باشه من يه روز ديه مي مونم
Will you give me your weapon ?
ميشه اسلحه تون رو بديد به من؟
Oh, Charlie ! I'm a lieutenant colonel, United States Army.
اوه ارلي من افسر ارشد نيروي ارتش آمريکا هستم
I'm not giving my fucking gun to anyone.
حاظر نيستم اسلحه خودم رو براي سوءاستفاده ديران به کسي بدم
- Now, what are you drinkin' ? - Colonel, this -- this is unacceptable.
خب حالا بو ببينم نوشيدني ي مي خوري؟ کلنل ...اين اصلا قابل قبول نيست
Unacceptable ? What are you givin' me that prep school crap for ?
قبول نيست؟توي داري بهم بدي که اون مدرسه بابتش داره بهم مي ده؟
What have they done, taken the Oregon out of the boy ?
اونها ه کار کردند فقط يه سري رو از ارون آوردنش اينجا؟
Put in Harvard Business School ?
براي دانشاه هاروارد سرمايه ذاري مي کنند؟
Then give me your bullets.
حداقل لوله هاتون رو بديد به من
You do see the sense of it, Charlie, don't you ?
متوجه شدي درسته؟
I can't chew the leather anymore.
ديه بيشتر از اين نمي تونم تحمل کنم
So, why should I share...
خب را من بايد خودم رو
the tribe's provisions ?
به مقررات قبيله اي مقيد کنم؟
I mean, there's no one...
منظورم اينه که وقتيکه کسي نمي خواد
wants to tear a herring with me anymore.
کمکي به من کنه، من را خودم رو توي عذاب بندازم
The bullets, Colonel.
لوله ها کلنل
"The bullets, Colonel."
" لوله ها کلنل "
You sound like a guy in "Lives of a Bengal Lancer."
تو بيشتر شبيه سر توي فيلم " زندي نيزه انداز بنالي "هستي
What do you give a shit for ?
با اين لعنتي مي خواي ه کار کني؟
About what ?
ي؟
About whether I blow my brains out or not.
اونه که توي مغزم وجود داره
- Because I have a conscience, you know. - You have a conscience.
بايد بدونيد که من هم وجدان دارم آره تو وجدان داري
I forgot.
يادم رفته بود
The Charlie Conscience.
وجدان ارلي
Do we tell ? Do we not tell ?
اينو فاش کنيم يا نه؟
Do we follow the rich boy's code or not ?
دنباله رو اون سر ولدار بشيم يا نه؟
Do we let this blind asshole...
اجازه بديم اين احمق کور
die... or not ?
بميره يا نه؟
Yeah.
جوابش مثبته
Conscience, Charlie.
وجدان، ارلي
When were you born, son ?
ه وقت دنيا اومدي، سر؟
Around the time of the Round Table ? Hah.
زمان فتوي آزاد و مسالمت آميز؟ هان
Haven't you heard ?
وشات نشنيدند؟
Conscience is dead.
وجدان مرده
No, I haven't heard.
نه من نشنيدم
Well, then, take the fucking wax outta your ears !
خب حالا بهتره که اون نبه رو از وشت بيرون بياري
Grow up !
بزر شو
It's fuck your buddy.
دوستت رو مسخره مي کني
Cheat on your wife.
همسرت رو فريب مي دي
Call your mother on Mother's Day.
روز مادر رو به مادرت تبريک مي ي
Charlie, it's all shit.
ارلي اينها همشون کار بيخوديند
Where you goin' ?
کجا مي ريد؟
I got piss call.
مي رم دستشويي
I know I said I need ya for just one day,
مي دونم که بهت فتم يه روز ديه بموني
but even I can't hold it that long.
اما بيشتر از اين ديه نمي تونم نهش دارم
Oh, and, Charlie,
ارلي
you forgot the one in the chamber.
اين يکي فشن يادت رفت
There you go, sir.
بفرماييد قربان
Thank you.
ممنونم
Twenty-six years in the service,
بيست و شش سال يش توي اين سلموني
never let an aide shine my shoes.
کسي نمي يومد کفش واکس نمي زد
Where you gonna be in 26 years, Charlie ?
ارلي تو وقتي 26 سالت بشه ه کار مي کني؟
Playing golf with your friends from the Baird School, I bet.
شرط مي بندم که اون موقع داري با همکلاسي مدرسه بيرد لف بازي مي کني
I don't even like those guys.
من علاقه اي به اون به ها ندارم
Course you don't. They're all assholes.
البته که تو دوستشون نداري اونها همشون احمقند
Be a pleasure to squeal on 'em, wouldn't it ?
از اينکه رابطه ات با اونها ندان خوب نيست،خوشحال نيستي؟
- Yeah, well, I'm not a squealer. - "I'm not a squealer."
را اما من که دشمنشون نيستم " من دشمنشون نيستم "
What is this, the Dreyfus case ?
حرفي که مي زني يعني ي؟
There you go.
بفرماييد
- Thank you.
ممنونم خواهش مي کنم
Watch your step.
جلوي اتون
I'm gettin' that heavy feelin' again, Charlie.
ارلي دوياره احساس سنيني دارم
There's more to this, isn't there ?
بيشتر هم ميشه درسته؟
Isn't there ?
درسته؟
- I was offered a bribe. - Oh, now we're cookin'.
بهم خواستند رشوه بدند خب اصلش هم همينه، ما هم اينکار مي کنيم
Mr. Trask, the headmaster,
مديرمون آقاي ترسک
he promised to get me into Harvard.
بهم قول داده که منو بفرسته هاروارد
- If you squeal. - Yeah.
اه راز دوستات رو فاش کني ي خب
What a dilemma.
اوضاع خيلي بدتر مي شه
Should Charlie Simms accept a free ride into Harvard or not ?
الان اين ارلي سيمس هست که بايد يشنهاد هاروارد رو قبول کنه يا اينکه نکنه
What do you think your friend George would do if he were in your shoes ?
اه دوستت جرج بخواد ا توي کفشت کنه ي؟
- He is, practically. - How ?
بعيد هم نيست طوري؟
I mean, it's just that Mr. Trask hasn't promised to get him into Harvard.
خب در حقيقت آقاي ترسک به اون قول هاروارد رو نداده
Mr. Trask doesn't have to. George's father's gonna take care of that.
معلومه که ترسک اين کار نمي کنه براي اينکه در جرج خودش اين زحمت رو مي کشه
Do the deal, Charlie. Take it !
اين معامله رو قبول کن ارلي
Go to Harvard.
برو به هاروارد
- I can't do that. - Why not ?
نمي تونم اينکار رو بکنم را نمي توني؟
It's just some things you just can't do.
دليلش يزهايي هست که شما نمي تونيد درک کنيد
Explain 'em to me.
برام توضيح بده ببينم
- Louder, please. - I, l, I can't --
بلندتر خواهش مي کنم من،من، من نمي تونم
You're gonna have a tough time in this world, Charlie.
ارلي تو در اين دنيا با مشکلات بيشتري بعدا برخورد مي کني
To ease the blow, let me buy you a drink. Come on.
سخت نير بيا بريم و يه نوشيدني بخوريم
[ Frank ] Double Jack Daniels on the rocks.
دو تا بطري جک دانيلز
And bring my young friend here a Shirley Temple.
و براي دوست جوانم هم شرلي تمل بياريد
Hold on. Do you have beer ?
يه لحظه صبر کنيد آبجو هم داري؟
Certainly. May I see some I.D. ?
البته مي تونم بعضي ار مارکها رو ببينم؟
Are you interested in walkin' the rest of your life, chappy ?
نمي خواييد که بقيه عمرتون رو توي خيابونها ز کنيد؟
Sir, but --
قربان اما
I'm a regular here. My boy's going on 23.
من آدم منظمي هستم اين سر هم 23 ساله ست
Why don't you call up front, the office ?
را نمي ري از مديرت نمي رسي؟ برو بهش زن بزن
Mr. Gilbert, he's a friend of mine.
آقاي يلبرت يکي از دوستان منه
Any particular beer ?
آبجوي خاصي مدنظرتونه؟
Schlitz. No Schlitz ?
شيليتز؟ نه شيليتز نه؟
Blatz. No Blatz ?
بلتز؟ بلتز هم نه؟
Improvise.
هر ي آوردي
- I'll do my best, sir. - [ Frank ] Thank you, sir.
اوامر شما رو الساعه اطاعت مي کنم ممنونم
You're human, Charlie. Beer ?
معرکه اي ارلي آبجو؟
Who are we drinking with ?
حالا با ه کسي نوشيدني بخوريم؟
I'm getting a nice soap-and-water feeling from down there.
يه بوي صابون معطري از اون ايين برام مي ياد
- Ah... female. - Female ?
از يه زنه زن؟
You're callin' her female, must mean you like her or you wouldn't be so casual.
وقتي که بهش مي ي زن يا دوستش داري ، يا اصلا برات اهميتي نداره
- Is she alone ? - Yeah, she's alone.
تنهاست؟ آره تنهاست
Things are heatin' up. Chestnut hair ?
مثل اينکه هيجانزده ست رن موهاش شاه بلوطيه؟
Brown... Light brown.
قهوه اي قهوه اي روشن
Twenty-two ?
بيست و دو ساله؟
Wh-- What am l, a guy at a carnival ?
من که نمي خوام توي کارناوال شرکت کنم
The day we stop lookin', Charlie, is the day we die.
روزي رو که بدون ديدن و جستجو تموم کنيم بهتره که در همون روز بميريم
Move.
اشو
- Where ? - You know where, son.
کجا؟ تو مي دوني کجاست
Don't be coy, Charlie.
ارلي خجالتي نباش
This woman is made for you. I can feel it.
اين زن براي تو ساخته شده مي تونم حسش کنم
Goddamn beautiful, isn't she ?
مثل فرشته ها زيباست، درسته؟
- She's not bad. - Whoo-bingo ! The boy's alive.
بدک نيست شاد باش خودت رو سرحال نشون بده
Come on, son, perambulate.
بيا سر يه دوري بزنيم
Perambulate.
بيا
Excuse me, senorita, do you mind if we join you ?
عذر مي خوام دوشيزه امکان داره ما ند در لحظه در کنار شما باشيم؟
I'm feelin' you're being neglected.
فکر کنم که شما رو فراموش کردند
Well, I'm expecting somebody.
خب من منتظر کسي ام
Instantly ?
تازه اومديد؟
- No, but any minute now. - Any minute ?
نه ند دقيقه مي شه؟ ند دقيقه؟
Some people live a lifetime in a minute.
بعضي از مردم واقعا در دقيقه ها زندي مي کنند
- What are you doin' right now ? - I'm waiting for him.
شما الان ه کار مي کنيد؟ من منتظرم
Would you mind if we waited with you,
امکان داره ما هم با شما منتظر باشيم
you know, just to keep the womanizers from bothering you ?
فقط مي خواييم با اين کار ديران مزاحم شما نشند
No, I don't mind.
نه مسئله اي نيست، بفرماييد
Thank you.
ممنونم
Charlie.
ارلي
You know, I detect... a fragrance in the air.
مي دونيد من مي تونم...بوهاي خوش و معطر رو در هوا حس کنم
Don't tell me what it is.
نيد که بوي يه
Ogilvie Sisters soap.
صابون اوليو سيسترز
Ah, that's amazing.
خيلي جالبه
I'm in the amazing business !
کار من جالبه
It is Ogilvie Sisters soap.
درسته بوي صابون اوليو سيسترز هست
My grandmother gave me three bars for Christmas.
مادربزرم به عنوان هديه کريسمس بهم داده بود
I'm crazy about your grandmother.
از مادربزرتون خوشم اومد
I think she'd have liked Charlie too.
فکر کنم اون ارلي رو هم دوست داشت
- Don't pay any attention to him. - What's your name ?
به اون توجهي نکنيد اسمتون يه؟
Donna.
دنا
- Donna ? I'm Frank. This here is -- - This is Charlie.
دنا؟ من هم فرانکم. اين هم ارلي
Yes. She likes you.
بله اون دوست داره
Charlie's having a difficult weekend. He's going through a crisis.
ارلي هفته بدي رو داشته بحران سختي رو شت سر ذاشته
How does he look like he's holding up ?
اصلا ديه براش قابل تحمل نبود طور مي تونست صبر کنه
He looks fine to me.
از نظر من سر خوبيه
Oh ! She does like you, Charlie.
اوه ارلي اون دوست داره
So, Donna,
خب دنا
do you tango ?
تانو مي رقصي؟
No. I wanted to learn once, but --
نه يه بار خواستم ياد بيرم اما
But ?
اما؟
But Michael didn't want to.
اما مايکل نخواست
Michael, the one you're waiting for.
مايکل، همونيه که منتظرشي
Michael thinks the tango's hysterical.
مايکل فکر مي کنه تانو آدمو عصبي مي کنه
Well, I think Michael's hysterical.
خب من فکر مي کنم مايکل خودش آدم عصبيه
Don't pay any attention to him. Did I already say that ?
به حرفاش توجهي نکنيد واقعا من اينو فتم؟
What a beautiful laugh.
ه لبخند زيبايي
Thank you, Frank.
ممنونم فرانک
Would you like to learn to tango, Donna ?
دنا مي خواي تانو ياد بيري؟
Right now ?
الان؟
I'm offering you my services... free of charge.
يادت مي دم بدون هزينه
What do you say ?
نظرت يه؟
I think I'd be a little afraid.
خب من يکم مي ترسم
Of what ?
از ي؟
Afraid of making a mistake.
مي ترسم نکنه اشتباه کنم
No mistakes in the tango, not like life.
در تانو هي اشتباهي وجود نداره مثل زندي که نيست
It's simple. That's what makes the tango so great.
ساده ست.کاري نداره رقص عاليه
If you make a mistake, get all tangled up, just tango on.
اه اشتباه کردي اصلا مهم نيست فقط به رقصت ادامه بده
[ Frank ] Why don't you try ?
را امتحان نمي کني؟
Will you try it ?
مي توني؟
All right. I'll give it a try.
بسيار خب امتحانش ضرري نداره
Hold me down, son.
منو ببر ايين سر
Your arm.
دستتون
Charlie,
ارلي
I'm gonna need some coordinates here, son.
من يه اطلاعاتي از اينجا مي خوام
The floor's about 20 by 30,
سالن حدود 20تا30 متره
And you're at the long end.
و شما هم در انتهاي سالن هستيد
There's tables on the outside. The band's on the right.
ميزها هم دور سالنه روه نوازنده هم در سمت راسته
Oh, Frank, you are one incredible dancer.
فرانک تو واقعا خارق العاده  مي رقصي
Wait'll you see Charlie dance.
بايد صبر کني تا رقص ارلي رو ببيني
- He's a liar. I don't dance. - Isn't he a charmer, though ?
اشتباه مي کنه، من رقصيدن بلد نيستم واقعا جذاب و زيبا نيست؟
Truth is, not only can he dance, but he'll sing you a hell of a tune.
حقيقت اينه که نه تنها مي تونه برقصه بلکه خواننده خوبي هم هست
He can do bird calls and imitate Bela Lugosi.
مثل بلبل برات مي خونه حتي مي تونه اداي بلا لووسي رو هم در بياره
- Hi, honey. - Hey.
سلام عزيزم سلام
Michael, this is Frank and this is Charlie.
مايکل، فرانک و ارلي رو بهت معرفي مي کنم
-Hi, Frank, Charlie. I'm sorry I'm late. -Oh, that's okay.
سلام فرانک، ارلي، ببخشيد اه کمي دير کردم اصلا مهم نيست
These two gentlemen entertained me,
اين آقايون از من ذيرايي کردند
and time flew.
اصلا ذشت زمان رو حس نکردم
Your girl is... a hell of a tango dancer.
دوست دخترتون خيلي خوب تانو مي رقصه
You found someone to tango with. That's terrific !
خلاصه يکي رو يدا کردي که باهاش تانو برقصي خيلي عاليه
Let me shake your hand.
بزاريد ازتون تشکر کنم
- No, it was Frank. - Hell, I'll shake both your hands !
نه اين فرانک هست مهم نيست از هر دوتاتون تشکر مي کنم
Honey, this looks like the place, but we gotta go.
عزيزم خيلي دوست دارم اينجا بمونيم اما بايد بريم
We got a date with Darryl and Carol in the village.
يه قرار ملاقات با داريل و کارول دارم
Do you have a check ?
دسته ک همراهت هست؟
- Michael, please. My pleasure. - No, no. I got this.
مايکل از ديدنتون خيلي خوشبخت شدم من هم همين طور
Michael, get your hand outta your pocket. I'll take it. Really.
مايکل دستهاتو از جيبهات بيار بيرون ورنه خودم اين کار رو مي کنم
Allow me.
اجازه مي ديد
Why, thank you.
را که نه ممنونم
Bye, guys.
خداحافظ آقايون
Bye.
خداحافظ
Darryl and Carol. Yeah.
داريل و کارول بله
[ Manny ] It's Apartment 17 E, Colonel. She's expecting you.
اين آارتمان 17 اي هست، کلنل اون خانم منتظر شماست
You don't have to worry about a thing. She's the creme de la creme.
اصلا نران يزي نباشيد اون خانم زيبا و دلرباييه
My buddy took the Vice Chancellor of Germany to her.
دوستم صدراعظم آلمان رو هم يشش برده
Now he wants to immigrate to this country.
حالا اون مرد مي خواد به اين کشور مهاجرت کنه
[ Frank ] You did good, hombre.
کارت عالي بود
My hair, how is it ?
موهام طوره؟ تيم خوبه؟
It's perfect.
بهتر از اين نمي شه
- I got the red foulard okay, didn't I ? - Yeah, real dark red.
يه دستمال قرمز براي لباسم خريده بودم، هستش؟ بله رنش هم جريه
Burgundy, Charlie, burgundy.
مارکش برانديه ارلي براندي
They love it.
ازش خوششون مي ياد
Bay Rum.
عطر هم بي رام هست
Windsor knot.
اين هم وينسدوري هست
[ Sigh ] That's my heart I'm feelin'.
واي قلبم احساس مي کنم که ديه
I'm off.
دارم مي ميرم
Can you get long distance on this ?
مي تونم از اين استفاده کنم؟
And how. Be my guest.
البته مهمون من باشيد
- Sugarbush lodge. - Hi. George Willis, please ?
شوربراش لوج سلام لطف کنيد جرج ويليس برام وصل کنيد؟
One moment, please.
يک لحظه لطفأ
- Hello ? - Ah, Harry ?
الو؟ هري؟
Chas, how are you ?
اس طوري؟
You just caught us. We're about to shoot George over to the airport.
وقتيکه تو با ما تماس رفتيم به جرج فتيم که بهتره بره فروداه
Why is George going to the airport ?
را جرج رفته فروداه؟
Um, hold on. Maybe you should talk to the man himself.
يه دقيقه وايستا ببينم نکنه تو به اون همه يز رو فتي
- Chas. - Yeah. Hi, George.
اس بله سلام جرج
- You just caught me. - Harry said. Where you goin' ?
من لو رفتم هري فت، کجا مي خواي بري؟
- Home. - To Boston ?
خونه بوستون؟
Catching the puddle jumper. Keep your fingers crossed.
دور و بر من نلکي ورنه روزارت رو سياه مي کنم
What are you going home for ?
براي ي مي خواي بري خونه؟
[ Sigh ] I was thinking, Chas. This asshole, Trask ?
فکر کنم اس کار اين مردک ترسک باشه؟
He's making no sense at all.
بويي از انسانيت نبرده
Somebody's gotta talk to him. My father's Class of '59.
يکي بهش همه يز رو تعريف کرده درم فهميده
Your father ? I thought we were gonna keep our parents outta this.
درت؟ من فکر مي کنم که والدينمون نمي دونند
This guy Trask is outta control, Chas. Outta control !
اين مردک ترسک که هي کنترلي نداره آدم بي اختياريه
Somebody's gotta talk to him.
يکي قضيه رو لو داده
- My father's a major fund-raiser, you know. - No, I didn't.
م يدوني که در من يکي از سهام داران مدرسه ست نه نمي دونستم
Just relax. He'll get us off the hook.
نران نباش اون مي دونه ه کار کنه
- I gotta go. Everything all right ? - Sure.
من بايد برمف اوضاع مرتبه؟ آره
- I'll see you Monday. Good-bye. - Bye.
دوشنبه مي بينمت خداحافظ خداحافظ
- Good night, sir. - Good night.
شب بخير آقا شب بخير
Hiya, Charlie.
سلام ارلي
Watch the door.
در رو باييد
What a beautiful woman.
ه زن زيباييي بود
- Hello, there. - Do you see what I see ?
سلام اونجاييد يزي که من مي بينم شما هم مي بينيد؟
[ TV ] Yeah. Either there's something wrong,
آره نکنه اتفاقي افتاده
or we got the world's worst hangover.
اتفاق بدي افتاده؟
Won't you come in ?
را نمي ياييد تو؟
Colonel ?
کلنل؟
Colonel, you all right ?
کلنل، حالتون خوبه؟
What is there ?
ي شده؟
It's afternoon. You've been sleeping all morning.
بعدازظهره شما تمام صبح خواب بوديد
So what ?
خب که ي؟
I don't know. I thought --
نمي دونم فکر کردم
I-l talked to George last night.
من ديشب با جرج صحبت کردم
His father's a big-deal alumnus at school. He's got a lot of pull.
درش نقش مهمي توي فارغ التحصيلي دانش آموزها داره خيلي نفوذ داره
Really ?
جدي؟
Yeah, he's, ah,
بله
he's gonna talk to the headmaster.
رفته و با مدير صحبت کرده
George thinks he might be able to get us off the hook.
جرج فکر مي کنه که بتونه ما رو از اين مخمصه نجات بده
"Get us off the hook."
ما رو از اين مخمصه نجات بده
Yeah, that's -- that's what he said.
بله يزي که خودش فت
Watch the "us" part.
به کلمه " ما" دقت کردي
Colonel, don't you wanna get up and do something ?
کلنل نمي خواييد از جاتون بلند شيد و کاري بکنيد؟
Colonel ?
کلنل؟
Oh, Charlie, what do ya want ?
اوه ارلي ي مي خواي؟
I don't know !
يزي نمي خوام
But you're making me nervous.
اما وضعيت شما منو ناراحت مي کنه
My wallet is on the dresser.
کيف ولم توي کشوي لباسه
Take out your plane ticket...
بليط هوايما خودت رو
and $400 mustering-out pay,
با 400دلار ول بردار
plus...
همين طور هم
airport-to-school taxi.
کرايه تاکسي فروداه به مدرسه رو بردار
Colonel, it's no rush. I mean, I can --
کلنل خيل ي عجله اي نيست منظورم اينه که مي تونم
I could stay for a while.
م يتونم يکم ديه بمونم
Charlie, you already gave me a day.
ارلي تو همين الانش هم يه روز ديه موندي
For that day, I am eternally grateful.
خيلي خوشبخت بودم که تو يه روز اضافه تر موندي
But right now I have... other plans.
الان من نقشه هاي ديه اي دارم
What other plans do you have ?
ه برنامه هاي ديه اي داريد؟
To die, son.
بميرم سر
Colonel, you're --
کلنل، شما
Come on, Colonel, you're not gonna die today.
کلنل بس کنيد شما امروز نمي ميريد
Charlie, give me your hand.
ارلي دستت رو بده به من
You go now, boy. Okay ?
حالا مي توني بري باشه؟
You go. Just, uh --
برو همين الان
Just leave me sleep here.
فقط منو تنها بزار مي خوام بخوابم
Look, uh -- Can we start over, please ?
ببينيد ما دوباره مي تونيم دو.باره شروع کنيم؟
What do you feel like doin' today, huh ?
ناه کنيد ببنيد که امروز ه حسي داريد؟
I mean, look at this. The sun is shining !
منظورم اينه که ناه کنيد که طور خورشيد به همه جا تابيده
It's a beautiful day. Let's --
ه روز زيبا و قشنيه
Colonel, I know you don't want to be a party poop,
کلنل نمي خوام امروزمون به بطالت بذره
so let's go out and do something, huh ? Let's go for a ride.
بياييد بريم و بيرون يه کاري بکنيم هان؟ مثلا بريم رانندي
Yeah, a ride.
آره رانندي
A ride ?
رانندي؟
Yeah, Colonel Slade, what do you say ?
بله کلنل اسليد نظرت يه؟
Let's go for a ride, huh ?
بزن بريم رانندي هان؟
What kind of ride ?
ه نوع رانندي؟
Yeah, this is a valid Oregon driver's license,
اين واهي مربوط به ايالت ارون هست
and we let appropriate customers test-drive the Testarossa.
ما فقط به مشتري هاي اهل تستاروسا اجازه رانندي مي ديم
But you're 17 and with a blind companion. That we don't do.
از طرفي شما 17 سالتونه و همراهتون هم يه فرد نابيناست نمي تونيم اين اجازه رو بهتون بديم
This is a $190,000 piece of machinery.
اين ماشين 190هزار دلار قيمتشه
- I'm not letting it out this door. - How 'bout this one over here ?
نمي تونم اجازه بدم که اين ماشين رو از اينجا ببريد بيرون اوني که اونجاست ه طور؟
That's a Cabriolet T. The same deal.
اون مدل کابريت تي شرايط اين هم همون طوره
Think I'm gonna let an unaccompanied kid get behind the wheel of a $110,000 car ?
فکرش رو بکنيد من ه طور مي تونم اجازه بدم که يه سر بدون همراه سوار ماشين 110هزار دلاري بشه؟
He will not be unaccompanied.
اون همراه داره
I'll be with him. I'm his father.
من همراهش هستم درشم
- You're his father ? - Yes.
شما درشيد؟ بله
I have an idea. Why don't I take your father for a test-drive ?
يه نظري دارم .ه طوره يه تست رانندي از ايشون بيريم
- What's your quota, Freddie ? - Don't worry about my quota. I do well.
ه تستس فردي؟ نران امتحان نباش
How many Ferraris you sold this month ?
ند ماشين فراري توي اين ماه فروختي؟
That's not relevant to this discussion.
اين ه ربطي به بحث ما داره
Freddie, the 80s are over.
فردي بالاي 80 تا
Are you tryin' to tell me these are just walkin' outta the store ?
تو م يخواي به من بي که اين کار خارج از مقررات فروشاه ست؟
This is a Ferrari, the finest machinery made in the automobile industry.
اين ماشين فراري اولين اتومبيل يشرفته صنعتيه
If you like it that much, why are you sellin' it ?
اه خيلي روي حرفت افشاري مي کني را نمي فروشيش؟
- I'd love to accommodate you -- - If this car performs the way I expect it to,
دوست دارم اين کار رو براي تو بکنم اه اين ماشين کارش خوبه، منتظرم
you'll get a certified check of $101,000 and change when in you come tomorrow.
يه ک 101هزار دلاري بهت مي دم که مي توني فردا نقدش کني
It's $109,000, plus $950, plus tax.
109هزار دلار به اضافه 950دلار و به اضافه تاکسي
Freddie, for you...
فردي به تو
107 all in,
107تا بيشتر نمي دم
plus a case of champagne to go with your leftover turkey.
به اضافه يه يلاش شاماني و وشت بوقلمون شب عيد
What do you say ? Don't worry about the boy.
نظرت يه؟ نران اون سر هم نباش
He drives so smooth, you can boil an egg on the engine.
خيلي با احتياط رانندي مي کنه جوري که مي توني توي موتور ماشين يه تخم مرغ رو آبز کني
When we bring the car back, I'll peel the egg for ya.
وقتيکه بررديم تخم مرغ رو برات وست مي کنم
Listen, you made me laugh, but I can't let the car go out.
وش کن تونستي منو بخندوني اما نمي تونم بزارم ماشين رو از اينجا ببريد بيرون
Want a deposit ?
بيعانه مي خواي؟
This is not an installment item, sir.
اين قسطي نيست آقا
Freddie, you're no spring chicken, are ya ?
فردي تو که آدم تازه به دوران رسيده نيستي؟
Well, you know what they call me at the home office ? The gray ghost.
مي دوني اينجا به من ي مي ند؟ روح بيرن
You know why they still keep me around ?
مي دوني را منو اينجا نه داشتند؟
There's no kid here that can move a Ferrari like I can.
هي به اي وجود نداره ،اونطوري که من مثل فراري حرکت مي کنم ،حرکتي کنه
I'm known from coast to coast like butter and toast.
اين ور ساحل تا اون ور ساحل رو به سرعت آب شدن کره روي نون مي رم
Ask anybody about Freddie Bisco.
برو از هم در مورد فردي بيسکو برس
When I get a Ferrari... out the door !
مي ند که وقتيکه سوار فراري بشم طوري در ميرم
- Hah ! You just made me laugh. - Yeah ?
واقعا منو خندوندي جدي؟
Two thousand.
دو هزار تا
Unless you take it, you're gonna make me cry.
اه اينو نيري همين جا ريه مي کنم
I'm a gray ghost too.
من هم مثل تو يه روح بيرنم
See ? This is fun, isn't it ?
مي بينيد؟ جالب نيست؟
- [ Engine Stops ] - Drop her into neutral.
خلاصش کن
Slide her into second. Pop the clutch.
برو دنده دو کلا رو هم بير
Straight. Hold it right like that. Feel it ?
صاف بيريد مستقيم، اينطوري
That's straight. Just keep it straight.
مستقيم فقط مستقيم و صاف نه داريد
- Keep it straight. - No fun just to keep it straight.
صافش کنيد مستقيم رفتم خيلي جالب نيست
You've got to move a little bit, feel the road.
يه ذره بيريد طرف خيابون
Please ? Just like this. All right ? There you go.
اينطوري خب؟ حالا بريد
[ Charlie ] Take it nice and easy.
راحته زود ياد مي يريد
Do you like this ?
خوشتون مي ياد؟
Slow it down a little. You goin' a little fast.
سرعتتون رو کم کنيد يکم تند کرديد
Colonel, slow it down.
کلنل آروم بريد
Something's happened to my foot !
مثل اينکه يه بلايي سر اهاي من اومده
- Slow it down, please. - Hold on, Charlie.
خواهش مي کنم آروم نران نباش ارلي
I think I've got another gear.
فکر کنم بايد دنده عوض کنم
Colonel Slade ?
کلنل اسليد؟
- Whoo-ah ! - Oh shit !
لعنتي
Watch out !
با
You'll get us killed !
داريد هر دوتامون رو به کشتم مي ديد
Don't blame me, Charlie. I can't see !
ازم ايراد نير ارلي نمي تونم ببينم
- Colonel, slow it down ! - [ Laughing ]
کلنل آروم تر سرعت رو کم کنيد
Oh, God. Oh, Jesus !
خداي من يا عيسي مسيح
Now let's see how this baby corners.
حالا ببين ه جوري مي رخه
- Corners ? - Yeah. Say when.
مي رخه؟ آره بو کي اين کار رو بکنم
- Say when what ? - Say when to turn.
ي رو بم؟ بو کي برخم
- Colonel, you can't turn the car. - Where's the turn, Charlie ?
کلنل شما نمي تونيد اين کار رو بکنيد به کدوم سمت ارلي؟
3:00 ? 2:00 ? Right oblique ? Right face ?
3؟2؟ انحراف يدا کنم؟ يا مستقيم؟
Come on ! Talk to me !
يالا بهم بو
Ah... it's left, I guess.
فکر کنم ...
Left. I knew it. Okay. Now ?
. مي دونستم خب. حالا ي؟
No, no ! Not now ! Not now !
نه نه الان نه نه
- Now ? - Colonel, please ?
حالا؟ کلنل خواهش مي کنم؟
Charlie, I'm gonna do it anyway. Whether you say so or not, here we go !
ارلي من هر جا مي تونم برم ه تو بي ه تو ني، س بهتره بي کدوم سمت
Okay ! Wait, wait, wait ! Just wait !
باشه فقط صبر کنيد صبر کنيد يه لحظه
Here I go.
دارم مي رم
Wait... now !
صبر کنيد... وايستا
I did it ! Oh, Charlie !
رفتم ارلي
You're ridin' with one very happy man !
تو با يه مرد شاد و بشاش اومدي رانندي
- Turn again ! - Be specific, son.
دوباره برخيد مشخصش کن به کدوم سمت
- Left now ! - Okay.
باشه
I love this !
من عاشق اين کارم
I love it ! Shall we take it to the max ?
عاشقشم ميشه با حداکثر سرعت رفت؟
Let me out.
بزار من برم
- [ Siren ] - Shit ! The yellow flag.
لعنتي ليس
I hadn't even opened her up yet.
تا به حال اينقدر با ماشين خوش نذرونده بودم
- Which way's the curb ? - Pull over. Slow down !
ه جوي ميشه نهش داشت؟ وايستيد.سرعت رو کم کنيد
- Slow down, Colonel. - All right, I'm doin' it.
آروم کلنل باشه دارم همين کار رو مي کنم
- Pull over to the curb. Slow it down. - Yep, yep. Got it.
آرو م بريد کنار ياده رو باشه باشه مي رم
- Oh, Christ. - Ooh, I haven't had a ticket in years.
خداي من توي اين ند سال مثل امروز برام نبوده
I'll do the talking.
باهاش صحبت مي کنم
License and registration.
واهي نامه و مدارک ماشين
What ? Are you test-driving this baby ?
ه خبر بود؟ داشتيد به اين به رانندي ياد مي داديد؟
Don't she purr though ?
صداي خرخر ماشين رو نشنيديد؟
At 70 miles an hour ?
70مايل در ساعت؟
You should hear her at 125. Hah !
بايد توي خيابون 125مي شنيديد
Where's your license ?
واهينامه تون؟
At the dealer's.
دست فروشنده ماشينه
They give it back when you return the car.
وقتيکه ماشين رو برردونم بهم سش مي دند
- You got I.D. ? - You bet.
کارت شناسايي طور؟ تو بردي
Indeed.
بفرماييد
Lt. Col. Slade.
افسر ارشد کلنل اسليد
And you, solider ?
و تو سرباز؟
The name is police officer Gore.
مامور ليس ور
Doin' a hell of a job, Gore.
شغل مزخرفي داري ور
And so are you, Colonel. Who's the kid ?
همين طور هم شما کلنل اون به کيه؟
My boy Charlie.
سرم ارلي
He kept tellin' me to "Let her out."
اون بهم فت که بزنم کنار
What was I gonna do, disappoint him ?
با کارم نااميدش کردم درسته؟
Yes.
بله
Tell you what I'm gonna do. I'm gonna let you go on one condition.
مي م مي خوام ه کار کنم به يه شرط مي تونيد بريد
- What's that ? - You take this rig straight back to the dealer.
ي؟ اين ماشين رو مستقيم برردونيد به فروشاهش
- Y-You got it. - Shut up.
بله هر ي شما بيد ساکت شو
- You want this ? - Sure. Gore ?
اينو مي خواييد؟ البته ور
Your face and your voice are familiar.
هره و صدات خيلي برام آشناست
You ever in the officer's club at Da Nang ?
تو هي وقت افسر ليس کلانتري دا نان نبودي؟
No.
نه
- Never in the army ? - No. Coast Guard.
توي ارتش طور؟ نه.توي ارد ساحلي بودم
Good Lord. Hah ! Hah !
.خداي بزر
Your dad is looking good, Charlie.
ارلي درت خيلي خوب مي بينه
He's got a heavy foot. Tell him to take it light. All right ?
اهاي سنيني داره بهش بو يکمي آرومتر بره
- I hear ya ! - Thanks.
اطاعت ممنونم
Get out of the car, 'cause you are not driving anymore.
ياده شيد بهتره که ديه شما رانندي نکنيد
Just keeping this baby warm, that's all.
فقط مي خواستم اينو يکمي رمش کنم همين
I'm not drivin' anymore.
ديه رانندي نمي کنم
Yes.
آره
- Take my arm. - I'm okay.
دستم رو بيريد حالم خوبه
- Colonel, it's really bumpy here. - Yeah, bumpy.
کلنل اينجا ر از دست اندازه آره دست انداز داره
You all right ?
حالتون خوبه؟
Yeah.
آره
Red light. Hold it.
راغ قرمزه وايستيد
Taking too long.
خيلي داره طول مي کشه
Shit ! Colonel ! Colonel ?
لعنتي، کلنل کلنل؟
Colonel !
کلنل
Shit ! You all right ?
لعنت حالتون خوبه؟
What the hell are you doing ?
ه کار مي کنيد؟ ي شده؟
- Take the cane. - I gotta take a piss.
عصا رو بيريد مي خوام برم دستشويي
- Take the cane, Colonel. - It happens to the best of us.
عصاتون رو بيريد کلنل هر دومون شانس آورديم
We're on Park Avenue. You can't go to the bathroom.
ما توي خيابون ارک هستيم شما که الان نمي تونيد بريد حمام
- Perfect place. - You'll get arrested.
جاي خوبيه نزديک بود دستيرتون کنند
Never been housebroken. Ohh !
را هي وقت مودبانه رفتار نمي کنيد
Shit !
!اي بابا
What's the matter with you, Colonel ?
کلنل تون شده؟
What are you doing ? Stand up.
ه کار مي کنيد؟ وايستيد
Come on.
بياييد اينجا
I'm tired, Charlie. I'm tired.
خسته ام ارلي خسته
Give me your arm.
دستت رو بده به من
Here's your cane.
عصاتون
Take me back to the hotel, son.
منو برردون هتل سر
Home at last.
بالاخره اومديم
You all right now ?
الان حالتون طوره؟
Yeah.
خوبم
- Do you want to use the bathroom ? - No.
نمي خواييد بريد حمام؟ نه
- Can I get you something ?
يزي نمي خواييد؟
- You sure you're all right ? - I'm fine, Charlie.
مطمئنيد حالتون خوبه؟ خوبم ارلي
Do you mind if I use the phone ?
اشکالي نداره از تلفن استفاده کنم؟
Go ahead.
ايرادي نداره
- Hello ? - Hi, is George there, please ?
الو؟ سلام مي خواستم با جرج صحبت کنم؟
Senior or Junior ?
سال آخر يا سال سوم؟
Junior.
سال سوم
- Who's this ? - A friend of his from school.
شما؟ يکي از دوستان مدرسه اش
George isn't going to be talking to any friends from school right now.
جرج الان نمي تونه با هي کدوم از دوستهاش صحبت کنه
- Oh. - Good-bye.
خداحافظ
Colonel, are you looking at me ?
کلنل شما به من ناه مي کنيد؟
I'm blind, Charlie.
من کورم ارلي
I'm gonna take a nap.
مي رم يه رت بزنم
Too much fresh air.
بايد يه حال و هوايي عوض کنم
It's probably a good idea.
فکر خوبيه
Want me to help you to your room ?
مي خوايي کمکتون کنم تا ببرمتون اتاق؟
No.
نه
Couch.
مي خوام برم روي تخت
I like this couch here.
تخت اينجا رو دوست دارم
You sure you're all right, Colonel ?
کلنل مطمئنيد که حالتون خوبه؟
I got a headache.
سرم درد مي کنه
Why don't you go downstairs, get me some Aspirin, Charlie ?
ارلي را نمي ري طبقه ايين براي من آسرين نمي يري؟
- Some Aspirin. - Yeah. Also...
آسرين آره خب
I feel like a cigar.
مي خوام سيار هم بکشم
Get me a couple of Monte Cristos, number one.
دو نخ سيار مونت کريستو درجه يک هم برام بير
- Monte Cristos, number one. - Yeah.
مونت کريستو درجه يک آره
You won't be able to get 'em at the newsstand downstairs.
تو که نمي توني بري از دکه روزنامه فروشي ايين بخري
So why don't you go over to...
س را نمي ري
Fiftieth and Fifth, Dunhill's.
به دکه خيابون 1550 دانهيل
Fella name of Arnold in the humidor.
اسم فروشنده اش آرنولد هست
Tell him, um, they're for me.
بهش بو که براي من مي خوايي
He'll know.
اون منو مي شناسه
You're back too fast.
خيلي زود برشتي
You didn't get my cigars, did you ?
سيارهامو خريدي؟
Get out of here, Charlie.
از اينجا برو بيرون ارلي
I thought we had a deal.
فکر مي کردم به توافق رسيديم
I welched. I'm a welcher. Didn't I tell you ?
زدم زير قولم.بدقولي کردم مه بهت نفته بودم؟
No, what you told me was that you gave me all the bullets.
نه، شما که به من فتيد همه لوله ها رو داديد به من
I lied.
دورغ فتم
- Yeah, well, you could have fooled me. - And I did.
آره با اين کارتون هم منو مسخره کرديد درسته
Charlie, how you ever gonna survive in this world without me ?
ارلي طوري بدون من مي خواي توي اين دنيا زندي کني؟
Why don't you just give me the gun, all right ?
را تفنتون رو به من نمي ديد؟
Wh-- What are you doing ?
ه کار مي کنيد؟
I'm gonna shoot you too.
به تو هم مي خوام شليک کنم
Your life's finished anyway.
بهر حال زندي تو هم تموم ميشه
Your friend George's gonna sing like a canary.
دوستت جرج هم بره با دمش ردو بشکنه
And so are you.
تو هم همينطور
And once you've sung, Charlie, my boy,
و زمانيکه تو بخواي آواز بخوني سرم
you're gonna take your place on that long, gray line...
در آراماه ابدي خودت جاي مي يري
of American manhood.
و مثل يه امريکايي شجاع مي ميري
And you will be through.
و سرنوشت تو ايننين خواهد بود
I'd like to disagree with you, Colonel.
من با کارتون مخالفم کلنل
You're in no position to disagree with me, boy.
تو در مقامي نيستي که با من بخواي مخالفت کني
I got a loaded .45 here. You got pimples.
تفن من ره، به سمت 45درجه هم نشونه رفته از طرفي تو هم عرق کردي
I'm gonna kill ya, Charlie, because I can't bear the thought...
مي خوام تو رو بکشم ارلي براي اينکه نمي تونم
of you sellin' out !
بي وفايي رو تحمل کنم
Put the gun down, all right, Colonel ?
تفن رو بزاريد زمين کلنل؟
What ? You givin' me an ultimatum ?
ي؟ داري به من التيماتوم مي دي؟
No, I'm --
نه نه
I give the ultimatums !
من به تو فرصت آخر رو مي دم
I'm sorry.
متاسفم
All right ?
باشه؟
It's all right... Charlie.
باشه ارلي
You break my heart, son.
تو قلب منو شکستي سر
All my life I stood up...
در تمام طول عمرم
to everyone and everything...
جلوي هر يز و هر کسي ايستادم
because it made me feel important.
براي اينکه اين حس برام خيلي مهم بود
You do it 'cause you mean it.
حالا تو اينکار رو کردي براي اينکه هدفت اين بود
You got integrity, Charlie.
ارلي تو کارت بي عيب و نقصه
I don't know whether to shoot ya or adopt ya.
نمي دونم بهت شليک کنم يا تو رو به فرزندي قبول کنم
Not much of a choice, is it, sir ?
هي راه ديه اي نيست؟
Aw, don't get cute now.
اصلا با اين قيافه زيبا به نظر نمي رسي
- Colonel, please put the gun away ? - I asked you a question.
کلنل خواهش مي کنم اسلحه رو بزاريد کنار؟ ازت يه سؤال رسيدم
Do you want me to adopt ya, or don't ya ?
مي خواي تو رو به فرزندي قبول کنم يا نه؟
Please ? I mean...
خب، مي خوام
- you're just in a slump right now. - Slump ?
فقط الان مي خوام شما عقي نشيني کنيد عقب نشيني؟
No slump, Charlie.
نه ارلي کنار نمي رم
I'm bad.
من آدم بدي ام
I'm not bad. No.
نه نه آدم بدي نيستم
I'm rotten.
من از درون وسيده ام
You're not bad.
شما بد نيستيد
Y-- You're just in pain.
شما...شما فقط درد کشيده ايد
What do you know about pain ?
تو از درد ي مي دوني؟
Hmm ? You little snail darter...
هان؟ تو فقط يه آدم بي دست و ايي
from the Pacific Northwest.
که از شمال غرب اقيانوس اشده اومده اينجا
What the fuck you know about pain ?
اصلا مي دوني درد ه يزعذاب آوريه؟
Let me have the gun, Colonel.
اسلحه رو بدينش به من کلنل
No time to grow a dick, son.
الان وقت بزر شدن نيست سر
Just, just give me the gun, all right, Colonel ?
فقط اسلحه رو بديد به من کلنل باشه؟
I'm talkin' a parade ground. Ten-hut !
دارم بهت دستور مي دم، سرجات وايستا
Soldier, that was a direct order.
سرباز اين يه دستور مستقيمه
Give me the gun ?
اسلحه رو بده به من؟
You can stay or you can leave.
تو هم مي توني بموني هم مي توني از اينجا بري
You understand ? Either way, I'm gonna do this thing.
فهميدي؟ هر راهي رو انتخاب کني من کار خودم رو مي کنم
Now why don't you leave and spare yourself ?
را از اينجا نمي ري و خودت رو نجات نمي دي؟
I want your gun, Colonel.
من اسلحه رو مي خوام کلنل
I'm gonna give myself a count.
من با خودم يه خورده حسابي دارم
You need a count for balance.
مثل اينکه تو هم براي اينکه بي حساب بشي بدت نمي ياد با من باشي
Five, four...
نج، هار
three...
سه
two...
دو
one. Fuck it.
يک. برو به جهنم
Gimme ! Fuck it !
لعنتي! لعنت به تو
- Get out of here ! - I'm stayin' right here !
از اينجا برو بيرون من همينجا مي مونم
- Get outta here ! - I'm stayin' right here.
برو بيرون همينجا مي مونم
- I'll blow your fuckin' head off ! - Then do it !
اه نري مغزت رو توي دهنت مي ريزم خب اينکار رو بکن
You want to do it ? Do it ! Let's go.
را اينکار رو نمي کني يالا زودباش
- [ Click ] - Fuck.
لعنتي
Get outta here !
از اينجا برو برو بيرون
You fucked up, all right ? So what ?
تو که همه يز رو نابود کردي، درسته؟ ديه ي مي خواي؟
So everybody does it. Get on with your life, would ya ?
با همه اينکار رو کردي زندي خودت رو هم نابود کردي درسته؟
What life ? I got no life !
کدوم زندي؟ من که زندي ندارم
I'm in the dark here !
من فقط توي تاريکي ام
You understand ? I'm in the dark !
مي فهمي؟ من توي تاريکي ام
So give up. You want to give up, give up...
س را دست از اين کارها بر نمي داري را دست بردار نيستي
'cause I'm givin' up too.
دليلش اينه که من مي خوام ديه ول کنم
You said I'm through. You're right.
بهم فتي که آخر خطم درست فتي
We're both through. It's all over.
هر دومون به آخر رسيديم همه يز تموم شد
So let's get on with it. Let's fuckin' do it.
س را تمومش نمي کني يالا زود باش
Let's fuckin' pull the trigger, you miserable blind motherfucker.
را ماشه رو نمي کوني تو فقط يه مادرمرده بدبختي
Pull the trigger.
شليک کن
Here we go, Charlie.
هر دوتامون ارلي
I'm ready.
من آماده ام
You don't want to die.
تو نمي خواي که بميري
And neither do you.
تو هم نمي خواي
Give me one reason not to.
دليلي برام بيار که نخوام
I'll give you two. you can dance the tango and drive a Ferrari...
دو تا دليل برات مي يارم هم مي توني تانو برقصي، هم مي توني سوار ماشين فراري بشي
better than anyone I've ever seen.
بهتر از هرکس ديه اي که تا به حال ديدم
You never seen anyone do either.
تو حتي نتونستي تا به حال کسي رو ببيني
Give me the gun, Colonel.
اسلحه رو بديد به من کلنل
Oh, where do I go from here, Charlie ?
خب بعد از اينجا کجا برم ارلي؟
If you're tangled up, just tango on.
اه تمومش کنيد مي تونيد بريد تانو برقصيد
You askin' me to dance, Charlie ?
ازم مي خواي که برقصم؟
§ Did you ever have the feelin' that you wanted to go §
تا به حال احساس کردي که دلت بخواد بري
§ And still had the feelin' that you wanted to stay §§
بعد هم از طرفي احساس کني که خواستي بموني
You like my blues, Charlie ?
از لباسم خوشت مي ياد؟
Yeah, they're beautiful.
آره قشنه
I wore these for Lyndon's inauguration.
اينو براي روز افتتاح ليندون وشيده بودم
Of course, uh, we weren't the number one ball.
البته ما فقط نبوديم
But he dropped by anyway.
اره اون از قدرت ساقط شد
Will you please give me the gun ?
ميشه ازتون خواهش کنم که اسلحه رو بديد؟
You're askin' an officer to surrender his side arm.
تو از من مي خواي که يه افسر يکي از دو بازوهاي خودش رو تسليم کنه
You don't have to surrender it. You just put it down for a little while.
شما مجبور نيستيد که تسليمش کنيد فقط ند لحظه مي زاريدش کنار
All right ? Just put it down.
باشه؟ فقط بزاريدش ايين
Boy, I could use a drink, Charlie.
سر، ارلي من عادت داشتم که يه نوشيدني بخورم
How about a cup of coffee ?
با يه فنجون قهوه طوريد؟
[ Laughs ] Too big a leap for me right now, Charlie.
س برو و برام يه بزرش رو بيار
Maybe tomorrow. Hah !
فردا هم باشه ايرادي نداره
No, a Mr. John Daniels would be preferred.
نه نه مشروب دانيلز رو ترجيح مي دم
No water, Charlie.
بدون آب ارلي
No water.
بدون آب
Please.
لطفأ
Here's your drink, Colonel.
بفرماييد کلنل
Oh. I'm so sorry.
خيلي عذر مي خوام
What time do you want me to turn down the bed ?
کي مي خواي که ملحفه هاي تختتون عوض بشه؟
- Uh, maybe later, all right ? - What he means, senorita,
بعدأ باشه بهتره سينوريتا منظورش اينه که
is come right in.
بياييد اينجا بهتره
- Later, please ? - Yes, sir.
بعدأ خواهش مي کنم؟ شم قربان
Good afternoon.
عصرتون بخير
Nice voice.
ه صداي زيبايي داشت
Boy, you have a one-track mind.
شما واقعا هوش فوق العاده اي داريد
Mm-hmm. Is there anything else in this world, Charlie ?
خب مه يز ديه اي هم توي دنيا وجود داره؟
- Not for you. - You know what's kept me goin' all these years ?
براي شما نه مي دوني ه يزي منو توي اين سالها نه داشته؟
The thought that one day --
فکر اينکه يه روزي
Never mind.
فراموشش کن
The what ?
ي؟
Silly.
احمقانه ست
Just the thought that maybe one day, I'd --
فقط فکر اينکه يه روزي
I could have a woman's arms wrapped around me...
بتونم يه زني رو توي بغلم بيرم
and her legs wrapped around me.
و اهاش بدور من بيه
And what ?
و بعد؟
That I could wake up in the morning and she'd still be there.
و وقتيکه صبح از خواب بيدار بشم اون هنوز اونجا باشه
Smell of her.
عطر و بوش رو حس کنم
All funky and warm.
رم و نرم
I finally gave up on it.
بالاخره يه روزي بايد دست بردارم
I don't know why you can't have that.
نمي دونم را نمي تونيد اون شرايط رو داشته باشيد
You know, when we get back to New Hampshire,
مي دونيد وقتي که بررديم نيوهمشاير
I don't know why you can't find someone.
نمي دونم شايد بتونيد يکي رو براي خودتون يدا کنيد
I mean, you're a good-lookin' guy,
منظورم اينه که شما يه مرد موفقي هستيد
and you're fun to be with, and...
و با هر کسي باشيد براي اون اوضاع خوب ميشه
you're a great travel companion, sensitive, compassionate.
شما يه مرد ماجراجوي نکته سنج و حساس و دلسوزيد
Charlie,
ارلي
are you fuckin' with me ?
داري منو دست مي ندازي؟
- Yes. - [ Phone Ringing ]
بله
Yeah ?
الو؟
Hey, Manny.
هي ماني تويي
My God. We -- We -- We missed our plane.
خداي من ، ما...ما از برناممون عقب افتاديم
Your plane, Charlie. My ticket was one-way.
برنامه تو ارلي بليط من يکطرفه بود
- New England Thruway all the way, Colonel ? - All the way, Rinaldo.
نيوانلند کلنل؟ درسته رينالدو
I'm gettin' that heavy feelin' again, Charlie.
ارلي دوباره من احساس سنيني دارم
I think you were right about George and his father.
فکر کنم در مورد جرج و درش حق با شما بود
- Uh, I'm sorry to hear that. - When we get back,
متاسفم که اينو مي شنوم وقتيکه بررديم
Mr. Trask is bringin' us up in front of the whole school.
آقاي ترسک ما رو جلوي دانش آموزهاي مدرسه مي بره
Puttin' your feet to the fire, huh ?
مي خواي با دم شير بازي کني؟
Special meeting of the Disciplinary Committee.
جلسه ويژه کميته انضباطي مدرسه
And what are you gonna tell 'em ?
خب ي مي خواي بهشون بي؟
I don't know. I'll think of somethin'.
نمي دونم خيلي فکر کردم
Oh, Charlie, why are you all alone in this thing ?
ارلي را اينقدر تو در اين مسئله تنهايي؟
Hmm ? Where's your father ?
هان؟ درت کجاست؟
He left.
اون ذاشته رفته
I thought it was a mom-and-pop store. Who's the "pop" ?
فکر مي کردم اون با مادرت فروشاه رو مي رخونه س اون کيه؟
- It's my stepfather. - Oh, yeah.
نادري ام درسته
But why isn't he in on this ?
خب را اون نمي ياد ؟
Somethin' wrong with him ?
رابطه ات باهاش خوب نيست؟
No, he's okay. We just, uh --
نه مشکلي ندارم فقط ما
- We don't get along very well. - Why not ?
به مدت طولاني با هم نبوديم را؟
- 'Cause he's an asshole. - Ah. Ha-ha !
براي اينکه آدم نادونيه
Well, that's all right, Charlie.
خب ارلي
Every family's got one nowadays.
هر خانواده اي براي خودش يه تازه به دورون رسيده داره
- That's it ? - That's it.
همين؟ همين
- Take care of yourself, kid. - All right, Manny. Thanks.
مراقب خودت باش سر ممنونم ماني
No, I'm not open.
در نزن که باز نمي کنم
I hate good-byes.
از خداحافظي متنفرم
So, uh, you'll be all right, huh ?
خب حالتون که خوبه؟
I'll be fine.
بهتر هم ميشم
All right.
خوبه
- [ Bell Ringing ] - What's that ?
ي بود؟
Uh, that's first bell.
اولين زنه
Just got time to get cleaned up.
بايد بريم و آماده شيم
Oh. I almost forgot.
فراموشش کردم
I owe you some money.
ولت يش منه
Three hundred dollars, hmm ? Job well done.
سيصد دلار درسته؟ در ازاي کار خوب
You ever need any references, Charlie,
ارلي تو هي وقت به کسي نياز نداري
- I'm your man. - Thanks, Colonel.
من شتتم ممنونم کلنل
- Uh, it's 16 Water Street. Just over the bridge. - We'll find it.
خيابون 16واتر بعد ل يداش مي کنيم
Good-bye, Charlie.
خداحافظ ارلي
Good-bye, Colonel.
خداحافظ کلنل
Come here, son.
بيا اينجا سر
Okay, Manny.
خب ماني
George. George !
جرج،جرج
I called an open meeting of this institution this morning...
خواستم امروز صبح در اين موسسه جلسه اي برزار بشه
because the incident that occurred this Tuesday last...
به دليل برخوردي که سه شنبه ذشته اتفاق افتاده
describes an issue that concerns all of us.
هممون هم مي دونيم ه اتفاقي افتاده
Not an isolated case of vandalism, what happened...
نه به خاطر يه خرابکاري
is a symptom of the sickness of a society,
بلکه به اين دليل که اين کار يه نشونه اي از بيماري اجتماعي هست
a sickness which runs counter to the principles...
بيماري که نظم و انضباط  اجتماعي رو نابود مي کنه
this school was founded on,
بيماري که در اين مدرسه يدا شده
a school, among whose graduates two have sat behind the desk in the Oval Office,
دقيقا هم در دو دانش آموزي که مي بينيد شت اين ميزها نشستند ديده شده
in the White House.
در اين مدرسه
Baird men have run state departments and investment houses,
دانش آموزان بيرد در بهترين مدرسه اين ايالت وارد شده و بر روي هوش و استعدادشون سرمايه ذاري مي کنند
founded department stores and coached football teams.
هزينه  خورد و خواب و خوراک رو به جون مي خرند و تيم فوتبال تشکيل مي دند
Our alumni receive their bulletins in ashrams in India...
نام فارغ التحصيلان ما در کشورهايي مثل هند و اردن
and in palaces in Jordan.
و در بهترين مقامها ديده مي شه
We are, in fact, known around the world...
در حقيقت ما در تمام دنيا شناخته شده ايم
as the cradle of this country's leadership.
ما در واقع مهد دانش اين کشوريم
- A beacon in the nation's -- - What are you doing here ?
و راغ هدايت ملتهاييم شما اينجا ه کار مي کنيد؟
- Got room for me up there, Charlie ? - But today,
ارلي مي توني يه جايي برام تهيه کني؟ اما امروز
- We are bleeding from disrespect, - Yeah, I guess so.
ما شاهد بي احترامي و بي حرمتي هستيم درسته من هم همينطور فکر مي کنم
- Give us a hand. - disrespect for our values...
يه جايي به ما بده بي احترامي عليه ارزشهامون
and a disrespect for our standards,
بي حرمتي عليه معيارها و الوهاي اجتماعي
a disrespect for the Baird tradition.
و اهانت نسبت به قوانيم و آداب مدرسه بيرد
And, as the custodians of that tradition,
و اکنون به عنوان متولي اين آداب و قوانين
we are here today to protect each other...
ما امروز در اينجا دور هم جمع شديم تا به همدير احترام بذاريم
from those who threaten it.
و از اونه که ما رو تهديد مي کنه رهيز کنيم
Who is this, Mr. Simms ?
آقاي سيمس ايشون کي هستند؟
- Uh -- - This is Mr. Frank Slade,
ايشون آقاي فرانک اسليد هستند
Lieutenant Colonel, United States Army, retired.
افسر ارشد ارتش ايالات متحده امريکا، البته بازنشسته
I'm here in place of Charlie's parents.
من در اينجا حکم والدين ارلي رو دارم
- Excuse me ? - In loco parentis.
ببخشيد متوجه نشدم؟ جانشين والدين
They could not make the trip from Oregon today.
اونها امروز نتونستند خودشون رو از ارون به اينجا برسونند
And what is your relationship to Mr. Simms ?
و نسبت شما با آقاي سيمس يه؟
Is this a courtroom ?
اينجا داداه ست؟
- Closest thing we could manage to it. - Then if we're taking oaths,
اينجا تقريبا شبيه داداه اداره ميشه خب اه بايد سوند بخوريم
there's a few people I'd like to swear in.
بايد بم که به ندرت يش مي ياد من به کسي قسم بخورم
There are no oaths at Baird. We are all on our honor.
کسي در بيرد قسم نمي خوره ما همه در اينجا انسانهاي باشرفي هستيم
Larry and Franny Simms...
لاري و فراني سيمس
are very dear, close friends of mine.
براي من خيلي عزيزند اونها از دوستان نزديک منند
They've asked me to appear here on Charlie's behalf.
از من خواستند که به جاي اونها بيام اينجا
Okay ?
نکته اي مونده؟
Happy to have you with us, Colonel.
از ديدارتون خيلي خوشحاليم کلنل
Mr. Willis.
آقاي ويليس
- Which Mr. Willis ? - George, Junior, sir.
کدوم يکي؟ دانشجوي سال سوم جرج
You were in a position last Tuesday night...
شما شب سه شنبه ذشته شما شاهد
to see who committed this act of vandalism. Who was it ?
يک خرابکاري در مدرسه بوديد خرابکاري کار کي بود؟
Well, uh, I have an idea who it was.
خب من بايد نظرم رو بم که ه کسي بوده
No, no, not an idea, Mr. Willis. Did you see or did you not see ?
نه نه نظر نمي خوام آقاي ويليس آيا شما اون فرد رو ديديد يا نه؟
Well...
خب
I-l didn't have my contacts in.
من اونقدر نزديک ماجرا نبودم لنزشمم رو هم نداشتم
Come on.
.دست بردار
I was in the library. I'd taken my glasses off,
من توي کتابخونه بودم عينکم رو برداشتم
and I was gonna put my contacts back in.
و اومدم بيرون و با اون صحنه مواجه شدم
I --
من
Then I helped Simms close up,
خب اومدم يش سيمس
and the next thing I know, we're outside,
بهدش هم تا اونجاييکه يادمه اومديم بيرون
and I hear this sound, and l, um,
يه صدايي شنيدم
didn't have any time to put my contacts in.
اونقدر وقت نداشتم که لنز رو روي شمهام بذارم و ببينم که ه خبره
Whom, with your limited vision, did you see ?
ه کسي جلوي ديد شما رو رفته بود که نمي تونستيد ببينيد؟
Like I say, it was blurry.
مي خوام بم منتها واضح نبود
I can't see without my contacts.
تا نزديک نمي شدم که نمي تونستم ببينم
What did you see, Mr. Willis ?
ي ديديد آقاي ويليس؟
What ?
ي؟
- What, you mean definitively ? - Stop fencing with me, Mr. Willis !
شما دقيقا منظورتون يه؟ با من بحث نکن آقاي ويليس
Tell me what you saw !
بهم بو ي ديدي
Now, don't hold me to this, but...
دستاه ام نکنيد
no contacts, it's dark...
نديدم تاريک بود
and everything, I mean --
يه يزي ، منظورم اينه که
- Mr. Willis ! - [ Willis Sighing ]
آقاي ويليس
Maybe...
شايد
Harry Havemeyer,
هري هيومير
Trent Potter and Jimmy Jameson.
ترنت وتر و جيمي جيمسون بوده
- Maybe ? - Ballpark, best guess.
شايد؟ اين حدس منه نمي دونم
[ Trask ] Could you provide us with some detail ?
مي تونيد جزيات بيشتري براي ما بيد؟
I mean, why don't you ask Charlie ?
خب را از ارلي نمي رسيد؟
I really think he was closer.
فکر کنم اون نزديکتر به ماجرا بود
Mr. Simms.
آقاي سيمس
[ Clearing Throat ] Yes.
بله
You don't wear contact lenses, do you ?
شما که به شمهاتون لنز نيست درسته؟
No, sir.
نه قربان
With your untrammeled sight, whom did you see ?
شما با اون ديد محدوي که توي شب داشتيد بيد که ه يزي ديديد؟
Well, I saw -- I saw something,
خب من يه يزي ديدم
but l-l-l I couldn't say who.
اما اما نمي تونم بم که کي بوده
[ Trask ] All right. What was the something you saw ?
بسيار خب شما ي ديديد؟
- I-l couldn't say. - You couldn't say or you wouldn't say ?
نمي تونم بم نمي تونيد يا نمي خواييد؟
Well, I just -- I --
خب من فقط من
- I just couldn't say. I'm -- - Couldn't, wouldn't, shouldn't.
فقط نمي تونم بم نمي تونم، نمي خوام، نبايد
You're exhausting my patience...
شما ديه داريد از صبر من سوء استفاده مي کنيد
and making a mockery of these proceedings.
و منو داريد توي اين جلسه مسخره و مضحکه مي کنيد
I will give you one last chance.
آخرين فرصت رو بهتون مي دم
The consequences of your response will be dire.
نتيجه اسخهاي شما خيلي خوشايند نخواهند بود
By dire I mean your future will be jeopardized permanently.
با اين جوابها مي دونيد که قطعا آينده شما به خطر مي افته
Now for the last time,
حالا براي آخرين بار
what did you see last Tuesday night...
شب سه شنبه ذشته
outside my office ?
بيرون از دفتر من ي ديديد؟
I saw somebody.
يه کسي رو ديدم
"l saw somebody." Good.
خوبه کسي رو ديديد
Did you see their size and shape ?
قد و اندازه اش رو ديدي؟
Yeah.
بله
And they were the size and shape of whom ?
ه قد و اندازه اي داشت؟
They were the size and shape --
قد و اندازه شون
of most any Baird student, sir.
بيشتر به دانش آموزهاي بيرد مي خورد
I am left with no real witness.
در واقع من يک شاهد حقيقي ندارم
Mr. Willis's testimony is not only vague, it is unsubstantiated.
شهادت آقاي ويليس نه تنها مبهم و نامفهومه بلکه قابل استناد هم نيست
The substance I was looking for, Mr. Simms,
اصل موضوع اينه که من بايد از آقاي سيمس برسم
was to come from you.
ما ماجرا رو بايد از شما بفهمم
I'm sorry.
متاسفم
I'm sorry too, Mr. Simms,
من هم براي شما متاسفم آقاي سيمس
because you know what I'm going to do,
مي دونيد که منظورم يه و ه کارهاي مي خواستم براتون انجام بدم
inasmuch as I can't punish Mr. Havemeyer,
حقيقت اينه که من نمي تونم آقاي هيومير
Mr. Potter or Mr. Jameson ?
وتر و جيمسون رو توبيخ کنم؟
And I won't punish Mr. Willis.
همينطور آقاي ويليس رو هم نمي تونم مواخذه کنم
He's the only party to this incident...
اون تنها بخشي از اين جريانه
who is still worthy of calling himself a Baird man.
کسي که هنوز شايستي اينو داره که بهش بند دانش آموز بيرد
I'm going to recommend to the Disciplinary Committee...
من به کميته انظباطي يشنهاد مي کنم
that you be expelled.
که بهتره شما اخراج بشيد
Mr. Simms, you are a cover-up artist...
آقاي سيمس خوب تونستيد روي قضايا رو بوشونيد
and you are a liar.
شما يک دروغو هستيد
But not a snitch !
اما خبرين نيست
Excuse me ?
ببخشيد؟
No, I don't think I will.
فکر نمي کنم مطمئنم
- Mr. Slade. - This is such a crock of shit !
آقاي اسليد ندتر از اين نمي تونستيد کار انجام بديد
[ Trask ] Please watch your language, Mr. Slade.
مواظب حرف زدنتون باشيد آقاي اسليد
You are in the Baird school, not a barracks.
شما در مدرسه بيرد هستيد نه سربازخونه
Mr. Simms, I will give you one final opportunity to speak up.
آقاي سيمس به شما آخرين فرصت داده ميشه تا اظهاراتتون رو کامل کنيد
Mr. Simms doesn't want it.
آقاي سيمس نمي خواد صحبت کنه
He doesn't need to be labeled...
نيازي به اين نداره تا برسب
"still worthy of being a Baird man."
دانش آموز مدرسه بيرد بودن رو روي خودش داشته باشه
What the hell is that ?
اين همه سروصدا براي يه؟
What is your motto here ?
اين ه نصيحتي هست که شما به بقيه ها مي کنيد؟
"Boys, inform on your classmates, save your hide;
سرها مواظب همکلاسي هاي خودتون باشيد و خودتون رو از اونها محافظت و مخفي کنيد
anything short of that, we're gonna burn you at the stake" ?
ار غير اين رفتار کنيد ما شما رو به صليب مي کشيم  و کشيم
Well, gentlemen,
خب آقايون
when the shit hits the fan, some guys run...
وقتيکه ند يه يزي در بياد بعضي ها مي استند و ناه مي کنند
and some guys stay.
بعضي ها هم از ا به فرار مي ذارند
Here's Charlie facin' the fire, and there's George...
د راينجا شما ارلي رو مي بينيد که در آتيش داره مي سوزه
hidin' in big daddy's pocket.
و در اونجا جرج توي جيبهاي درش مخفي شده
And what are you doin' ?
بعدش شما ه کار مي کنيد؟
You're gonna reward George...
شما از جرج قدرداني مي کنيد و بهش جايزه مي ديد
and destroy Charlie.
و ارلي رو نابود مي کنيد
-Are you finished, Mr. Slade ? -No, I'm just gettin' warmed up.
حرفهاتون تموم شد آقاي اسليد؟ نه من تازه دارم رم مي شم
[ Slade ] I don't know who went to this place.
من نمي دونم ه کساني تا به حال وارد اين مدرسه شدند
William Howard Taft, William Jennings Bryant,
ويليام هاوارد تفا ويليام جنينز برايانت
William Tell, whoever.
ويليام تيل يا هر کس ديه اي
Their spirit is dead, if they ever had one.
قطعاروح اونها نابود شده و مردند البته اه روحي در وجودشون بوده
It's gone.
مسئله اينجاست
You're buildin' a rat ship here,
شما در اينجا داريد يک کشتي شکسته رو مي سازيد
a vessel for seagoin' snitches.
کشتي که جز بدي و خباثت يز ديه اي در اون نيست
And if you think you're preparin' these minnows for manhood,
و اه شما فکر مي کنيد که اينها رو داريد مردان شجاع و با عرضه اي در مي ياريد
you better think again,
بهتره که تجديد نظر کنيد
because I say you are killin' the very spirit...
براي اينکه داريد روح اين سرها رو نابود مي کنيد
this institution proclaims it instills.
موسسه اي که فقط ادعا مي کنه
What a shame.
واقعا شرم آوره
What kind of a show are you guys puttin' on here today ?
ببينيد امروز ه نمايشي براي اين سرها برزار مي کنيد؟
I mean, the only class in this act is sittin' next to me.
بجاي اينکه الان سر کلاسهاشون باشند نشوندينشون اينجا به حرفهاي من وش بدند
I'm here to tell you this boy's soul is intact.
من اينجا بهتون مي م که تنها روح اين سر در وجودش هست
It's non-negotiable. You know how I know ?
و اصلا هم ذاتش تغيير نمي کنه مي دونيد که منظورم يه؟
Someone here, and I'm not gonna say who, offered to buy it.
يکي در اينجا هست که من نمي خوام بم که ي مي خواست معامله کنه
- Only Charlie here wasn't sellin'. - Sir, you're out of order.
فقط اينو بم که ارلي فروشي نيست آقا شما بيش از حد خودتون صحبت مي کنيد
I show you out of order.
بهت نشون مي دم که حد و حدود يه
You don't know what out of order is, Mr. Trask.
آقاي ترسک شما نمي دونيد حد و حدود يه
I'd show you, but I'm too old,
بهت نشون مي دادم اما حيف که خيلي ير شدم
I'm too tired, too fuckin' blind.
خيلي خسته ام فقط هم به خاطر اين کوري لعنتيه
If I were the man I was five years ago, I'd take...
اه من نج سال يش به اينجا مي اومدم
a flamethrower to this place !
حتما اينجا رو به آتش مي کشيدم
Out of order ? Who the hell you think you're talkin' to ?
حد و حدود؟ کي ديه جرات مي کنه در مورد حد با من بحث کنه؟
I've been around, you know ?
مي دونيد که من هم زماني بودم
There was a time I could see.
و مي تونستم ببينم
And I have seen.
و الان هم مي بينم
Boys like these, younger than these,
زماني سرهايي هم سن و سال اينها بلکه جوونتر
their arms torn out, their legs ripped off.
توي ميدونهاي جن دست و اهاي خودشون رو از دست مي دادند
But there is nothin' like the sight...
اما هي وقت به شم نديدم
of an amputated spirit.
که روحي در بدن نداشته باشند
There is no prosthetic for that.
هي وقت هم جاي روح خودشون يز ديه اي جايزين نکردند
You think you're merely sendin' this splendid foot soldier...
شما فکر مي کنيد که به جاي اهاي خوداين سرباز فقط کافيه
back home to Oregon with his tail between his legs,
يک اي زيبا و ر رزق و برق به ايالتش بفرستي تا جايزين اونها بشه
but I say you are...
اما من به شما مي م که
executin' his soul !
شما روحش رو کشتيد
And why ?
را؟
Because he's not a Baird man.
براي اينکه اون جزو به هاي بيرد نيست
Baird men. You hurt this boy,
سرهاي بيرد شما اين سر رو اذيت کرديد
you're gonna be Baird bums, the lot of you.
فقط مي خواييد اين سرها توي جامعه يه مشت مفت خور به بار بياند
And, Harry, Jimmy,
هري، جيمي
Trent, wherever you are out there,
ترنت، اينجا يا هر جاي ديه که هستيد
- fuck you too ! - [ Gavel Pounding ]
لعنت به همتون
Stand down, Mr. Slade !
آقاي اسليد بنشينيد
I'm not finished.
من حرفهام تموم نشده
As I came in here, I heard those words:
وقتيکه اومدم اينجا يه جمله اي شنيدم
"cradle of leadership."
"مهد و هواره رهبران"
Well, when the bough breaks,
خب وقتيکه شاخه اي بشکنه
the cradle will fall, and it has fallen here.
اون هواره و مهدتون مي افته و به دنبالش هم هر يزي که در اون هست سقوط مي کنه
It has fallen.
در واقع اين سقوط کرده
Makers of men, creators of leaders.
اي سازنده مردان اي آفريننده رهبران
Be careful what kind of leaders you're producin' here.
مواظب باشيد که ه رهبراني رو در اينجا رورش مي ديد
I don't know if Charlie's silence here today...
نمي دونم را ارلي امروز ساکت نشسته
is right or wrong; I'm not a judge or jury.
نمي دونم کارش درسته يا نه البته من قاضي نيستم و نمي تونم قضاوت کنم
But I can tell you this:
اما من بهتون مي م که
he won't sell anybody out...
اون هرز خودش رو نمي فروشه تا
to buy his future !
بتونه آينده اي براي خودش بخره
And that, my friends, is called integrity.
بايد بدونيد دوستان به اين مي ند درستي و کمال
That's called courage.
شجاعت
Now that's the stuff leaders should be made of.
الان اين کسيه که بايد ازش رهبري ساخته بشه
Now I have come to the crossroads in my life.
الان من در زندي ام به يه دوراهي برخوردم
I always knew what the right path was.
اما هميشه راه درست رو مي دونستم
Without exception, I knew, but I never took it.
بدون استثنا مي دونستم يه اما هي وقت انتخابش نکردم
You know why ?
مي دونيد را؟
It was too damn hard.
براي اينکه خيلي سخت بود
Now here's Charlie. He's come to the crossroads.
حالا اينجا ارلي وارد اون دو راهي شده
He has chosen a path.
يک مسير رو انتخاب کرده
It's the right path.
مسير درست
It's a path made of principle...
مسيري که از روي نظم و اصول هست
that leads to character.
و اون رو به داشتن شخصيتي مهم هدايت مي کنه
Let him continue on his journey.
بهش اجازه بديد بقيه دادرسي خودش رو انجام بده
You hold this boy's future in your hands, Committee.
اعضاي محترم کميته انضباطي، شما آينده اين سر رو در دستهاي خودتون داريد
It's a valuable future,
يک آينده ارزشمند
believe me.
حرفم رو باور کنيد
Don't destroy it. Protect it.
اونو از بين نبريد ازش محافظت کنيد
Embrace it.
حمايتش کنيد
It's gonna make you proud one day, I promise you.
بهتون قول مي دم يه روزي به خاطر اينکار به خودتون مي باليد
How's that for cornball ?
طور بود؟
Nothing can shut them up, sir.
قربان يزي نمي تونه اونها رو ساکت کنه
The Disciplinary Committee will take this matter under advisement...
کميته انضباطي طي يک جلسه خصوصي در مورد اين
in closed session.
موضوع تصميم يري مي کند
- What are they doin', Charlie ? - I think they're going to come to a decision now.
اونها ه کار مي کنند ارلي؟ فکر کنم الان ديه تصميمشون رو اعلام کنند
Very well.
خيلي خوبه
Apparently, that meeting will be unnecessary.
ظاهرأ اين جلسه ضروري نبوده
Mrs. Hunsaker.
خانم هانسکر
The joint student-faculty Disciplinary Committee...
اعضاي مشترک کميته انضباطي مدرسه
needs no further sessions.
به برزاري جلسات بعدي نيازي ندارد
They have come to a decision.
تصميم کميته به شرح ذيل مي باشد
Misters Havemeyer, Potter and Jameson...
آقايان هيومير، وتر و جيمسون
are placed on probation...
به دليل مظنون بودن به اعمال رفتار غير اخلاقي
for suspicion of ungentlemanly conduct.
مورد آزمايش حسن رفتار قرار مي يرند
It is further recommended that Mr. George Willis, Jr....
همنين براي اين کميته هنوز مشخص نرديده که آقاي جرج ويليس
receive neither recognition nor commendation...
در انجام اين کار همکاري داشته
for his cooperation.
و از اتهام مبرا مي باشند
Mr. Charles Simms is excused...
آقاي ارلزسيمس هم
from any further response to this incident.
از دادن هر ونه اسخي در مورد اين حادثه مبرا مي باشند
Charlie !
زنده باد ارلي
- Last step. - I can always count on you, Charlie.
آخرين قدم من هميشه مي تونم روي تو حساب کنم ارلي
[ Woman ] Colonel.
کلنل
I'm Christine Downes, Colonel Slade.
کلنل اسليد ،من کريستين دون هستم
I teach Political Science.
علوم سياسي تدريس مي کنم
I wanted to tell you how much I appreciate...
مي خواستم بهتون بم که کارتون واقعا عالي بود مي خواستم ازتون تشکر کنم
- your coming here and speaking your mind. - Thank you. Are you married ?
شما اومديد اينجا و واقعا از روي وجدان صحبت کرديد ممنونم .شما ازدواج کرديد؟
Went to a artillery school at Fort Sill with a Mickey Downes.
رفتي به مدرسه نظام در فورت سيل و با ميکي دون يه نسبتهايي داري
Thought he might've snagged you.
فکر کنم ديه بايد جلوت رو بيره
Uh, no, no, I'm afraid not.
نه نه فکر نکنم بتونه
Uh, Colonel Slade was on, uh,
کلنل اسليد هم
Lyndon Johnson's staff, Miss Downes.
با خانم  دون توي ستاد ليندون جانسون بوده
Were you ? Fascinating.
جدي مي يد؟ واقعا جالبه
We should get together, talk politics sometime.
ما بايد بعضي اوقات با هم در مورد سياست بحث کنيم
Fleurs de rocailles.
فلورس دروکايلس به خودت زدي
Yes.
بله
"Flowers from a brook."
"لهاي رودخانه اي"
That's right.
درسته
Well, Miss Downes,
خب خانم دون
I, I'll know where to find you.
اميدوارم دوباره شما رو ملاقات کنم
Charlie.
ارلي
- [ Charlie ] Bye, Miss Downes. - Bye.
خداحافظ خانم دون خداحافظ
You don't have to tell me, Charlie.
بهم نو ارلي
5'7",
قد7'5
auburn hair,
موهاي قهوه اي مايل به قرمز
beautiful brown eyes.
شمان قهوه اي زيبا
Manny.
ماني
Aw, Colonel, this is too much.
کلنل اين خيلي زياده
You earned it. Next time Charlie and l...
درآمدت همينه دفعه ديه من و ارلي
want to take a breather to New York, we're gonna call you.
وقتيکه خواستيم بريم نيويورک ردش به تو حتما اطلاع مي دم
You can drive us both ways.
تو مي توني ما رو هرجايي ببري
You're on. Not only will it be an honor,
هر ي شما بيد.اينکار خيلي براي من ارزش داره
I'll give you a rate.
حتي نمي تونم به خودم اجازه بدم کرايه رو يش دستي کنم
I'll see your rate and raise you.
در آينده تو رو خواهيم ديد
Stay outta harm's way, Manny.
ماني از خودت مراقبت کن
- Take care, Colonel. - You too.
مراقب خودتون باشيد کلنل تو هم همينطور
- Ready ? - No, thanks, Charlie. I'll take it from here.
حاضريد؟ نه ممنونم ارلي از اينجا به بعد رو خودم مي رم
You go on ahead. Manny'll drive you back to your dorm.
تو بهتره که بري ماني تورو به خواباهت مي رسونه
Come by before you go home for Christmas.
قبل از اينکه براي کريسمس بري بيا ببينمت
We'll have a little cheer.
اوقات خوش کوتاهي با هم مي تونيم داشته باشيم
And if you like, stay for dinner.
اه دوست داشته باشي مي توني براي شام هم بموني
Sometimes she cooks a pot roast.
بعضي وقتها کبابهاي خوبي درست مي کنه
It's almost edible.
قابل خوردنه
All right, Colonel.
باشه کلنل
- That'd be really -- - Bye, Charlie.
بسيار خب خداحافظ ارلي
Who's there ?
کي اونجاست؟
- That you, Francine ? - Yes.
تويي فرانسين؟ آره
- What are you doing ? - Taking a ride.
ي کار مي کني؟ دورخه سواري
Taking a ride ? What about you giving me a lift ?
دورخه سواري؟ مي يايي منو ببري بالا؟
- No. - No ?
نه نه؟
Aw, come on, Francine.
بيا فرانسين
We should make up. Don't you think it's time we made up ?
بايد يه يزي درست کنيم فکر نمي کني ديه الان وقتشه؟
- [ Francine ] No. - [ Slade ] Francine ?
نه فرانسين؟
- What ? - Your Uncle Frank's had himself...
يه؟ عمو فرانکت هم براي خودش
a really hard Thanksgiving weekend.
شکرزاري خوبي داشت
- [ Willie Muttering ] - What's that ?
اين يه؟
I hear a chipmunk.
صداي يه سنجاب کوولو رو شنيدم
Is it a walrus ?
اين يه شير ماهيه؟
No, it's Willie.
نه ويليه
Willie, why don't you help me with my bag ?
ويلي را کمکم نمي کني با هم کيفم روببريم بالا؟
Come on, son. Help me with my bag.
بيا سر بيا با هم کيف رو ببريم
Come on. Come on.
بيا بيا
You got it. Hold onto it. You're strong.
رفتيش.نهش دار آفرين قدر قوي و ر زوري
Come on.
بيا
Here we are.
رسيديم
Francine, come on with me and Willie.
فرانسين تو هم با من و ويلي بيا تو
I'll let you make me some marshmallow chocolate.
بهت اجازه مي دم شيريني شکلاتي بخوري
- Whaddaya say ? - Okay.
راست مي ي؟ البته